<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Following collections or pious little treatises together with the Rule of S. Clare and declarations upon it, are printed for the use of the English Poor Clares in Ayre an index whereof  begin's in the sequent page.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1401A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42495</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282119</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84657)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2227:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Following collections or pious little treatises together with the Rule of S. Clare and declarations upon it, are printed for the use of the English Poor Clares in Ayre an index whereof  begin's in the sequent page.</title>
                  <author>Clare, of Assisi, Saint, 1194-1253. Regula. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 128, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Michael Mairesse, permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Doüay :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poor Clares --  Spiritual life.</term>
               <term>Monasticism and religious orders --  Discipline.</term>
               <term>Monasticism and religious orders --  Rules.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150050:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FOLLOWING COLLECTIONS OR PIOUS LITTLE TREATISES, TOGETHER WITH THE RVLE OF S. CLARE AND DECLARATIONS VPON IT, Are printed for the uſe of the ENGLISH POOR CLARES IN AYRE. An Index whereof begin's in the ſequent page.</p>
            <q>This shall be unto you a direct Way. <bibl>Iſ. 35. v. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>You shall not decline, neyther to the right hand, nor to the left. <bibl>Deut. 5. v. 32</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> † <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at Doüay by MICHAELL MAIRESSE.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="license">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PERMISSV SVPERIORVM:</hi> 
                     <date>1684.</date>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150050:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150050:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE CONTENTS IN THE ENSUING BOOK.</head>
            <list type="contents">
               <head>I. A Pious Collection of ſeverall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable directions and devotions, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ENGLISH POOR CLARES, in order to the better obſervance of their holy <hi>Institute:</hi> very uſefull and neceſſary for all Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, both men and woemen.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Morning exerciſe for every day in the week. p. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From the riſing untill the work houſe. p. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In dreſſing your ſelf, ſeverall praiers. p. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A morning purpoſe. p. <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From the workhouſe till dinner. p. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>From dinner till the examin at night. p. <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Before ſleeping, prayers. p. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150050:3"/>
               <item>A direction how to ſay the way to Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. p. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to apply the ſeaven words, Chriſt ſpoake upon the Croſs. p. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>7.</hi> Ave's which are to be read for the <hi>7.</hi> ſorrows of our B. Lady: how they are to be ſaid. p. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations on the <hi>3.</hi> Pater's and Ave's which are ſaid at the shewing of the B. Sacrament. p. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>After your examin at night, how to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute our Lady with <hi>3.</hi> Ave's. p. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to ſay your Pater's and Ave's in thanks giving to Allmighty God for his benefits, for night or any other time. p. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An exerciſe for Maſs. p. <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certain Intentions or Meditations which we ought to have when we communicate: out of S. Bonaventure. p. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations before Communion: taken out of the ſame Saint. p. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Four conſiderations of S. Mathildis before Communion. p. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150050:3"/>
               <item>A Praier before, and another after receav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the B. Sacrament. p. <hi>39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What we ought to do, the day we commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate. p. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer before and after confeſſion. p. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Directions how to ſay the divine Office with due devotion and attention. p. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certain holy Meditations of the <hi>7.</hi> effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of blood: diſtributed for the canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hours. p. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A direction for mentall Praier. p. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Instruction for mentall Praier. p. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colloquies or ſpeeches, part in meditation, and part in Praier: praiſing Allmighty God's excellency, goodneſs, holyneſs, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſs, &amp;c. p. <hi>67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cauſes of diſtractions. p. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The means to reſiſt diſtractions of heart and tediouſneſs of spirit. p. <hi>69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The chiefest effects of praier. p. <hi>70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Things to be conſidered in meditating the Paſſion of our Saviour. p. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Severall Affections to be drawn from the
<pb facs="tcp:150050:4"/> conſideration of the ſame Paſſion. p. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations of the knowledge of ones ſelf. p. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations of ſin. p. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to conſider death. p. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the pains of the damned. p. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to contemplate Heaven. p. <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to conſider vertue. p. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to conſider the feaſts of Saints. p. <hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to meditate on the perfections of All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. p. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations of all Gods creatures in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. p. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſiderations of Gods creatures in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. p. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefits in brief of Allmighty God. p. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What you ought to do in the time to come with God's benefits in particular. p. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of our Redemption. p. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of our Vocation. p. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of our Iuſtification. p. <hi>79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of donation. p. <hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The benefit of Preſervation. p. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150050:4"/>
               <item>The benefit of glorification. p. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The eight Beatitudes. p. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Religious perſon ought often to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the benefit of his vocation, by theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances: Vnde es? Quo? Quomodo? Quando? Quo fine vocatus? p. <hi>84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Priviledges and benefits of a Religious Perſon. p. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Ieſus, Maria. Certain aspirations, for every day in the week. p. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Aſpirations for every day in the week, upon the Paſſion of our B. Saviour. p. <hi>92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Oblation unto our <hi>B.</hi> Lady, to ſay on any of her feaſts <hi>70</hi> Ave Maria's, and then during every day 5. Ave's and the praiers there following. p. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer to Ieſus Chriſt. p. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When you paſs by the B. Sacrament a prayer. p. <hi>100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When you take holy water. p. <hi>101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How to honour the B. Virgins Name. p. <hi>101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Litanies of our holy Father S. Francis. p. <hi>104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Litanies of our B. Mother S. Clare. p. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150050:5"/>
               <item>Litanies for the converſion of England. p. <hi>108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A dayly exerciſe of prayers, with weekly meditations upon the Paſſion. p. <hi>113</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meditations upon the Paſſion for every day in the week. p. <hi>117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A method for meditation. p. <hi>123</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer before meditation. p. <hi>124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer after meditation. p. <hi>125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Table of daily Patrons, Meditations, Vertues, Vices, and Intentions. p. <hi>126</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list type="contents">
               <head>II. A Short treatiſe concerning the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of à Religious life, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by S. BONAVENTURE to his devout Siſters.</head>
               <item>The Preface. p. <hi>3</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> By what means a man may attain to the true knowledge of himſelf. p. <hi>8</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of humility, and the ſtepps
<pb facs="tcp:150050:5"/> or degrees by which it is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd. p. <hi>14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of Religious poverty. p. <hi>22</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of ſilence, and how neceſſary it is to all Religious. p. <hi>30</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of the study of Prayer. p. <hi>35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> A remembrance of Christ's Paſſion. p. <hi>44</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Of the perfect love of God. p. <hi>54</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Of finall perſeverance. p. <hi>57</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list type="contents">
               <head>III. The Rule of the holy Virgin S. CLARE, faithfully tranſlated into English.</head>
               <item>The Apostolicall Confirmation of the Rule. p. <hi>3</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Of the rule and forme of life of the order of the poor ſiſters, given by S. Francis.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of thoſe who deſire to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Religion: and how they shall be received. p. <hi>6</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150050:6"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the divine office, of Faſting, of Confeſſing and Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. p. <hi>10</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of the election of the Abbeſs. p. <hi>11</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP 5.</hi> Of ſilence, and of the manner of speaking at the ſpeak-houſe, and Grate. p. <hi>14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> How the ſiſters may not receive any poſſeſſions, by themſelves or by any perſon interpoſed. p. <hi>16</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> The manner that the ſisters shall obſerve in their manuall works. p. <hi>18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> How the ſiſters shall not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate any thing to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: and of the ſick ſiſters. p. <hi>19</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> Of penance to be enjoined the ſiſters that offend: and of the manner of converſing without the Monaſtery. p. <hi>21</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Of the Admonishment and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the ſiſters. p. <hi>23</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150050:6"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 11.</hi> Of the duty of the Portreſs. p. <hi>24</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> Of the viſitour and Chaplin. p. <hi>26</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The reſt of the Bull for the Confirmation of the Rule. p. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Testament of our holy Mother S. Clare. p. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Our holy Mother S. Clar's Benediction unto her ſiſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and to come. p. <hi>36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Bull of Pope Innocent the fourth: that the Religious may not be conſtrain'd to receive Rents or Poſſeſsions. p. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list type="contents">
               <head>IV. The Declarations and Ordinances made upon the Rule of our holy Mother S. Clare.</head>
               <item>A letter of the Approbation and Confirmation of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, ſent by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend
<pb facs="tcp:150050:7"/> Father William Caſſall, to his devout daughter S. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let. p. <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another by the ſame Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father, to Siſter Collet, and all the other Siſters of the ſaid Religion. p. <hi>5</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Of the entry into this holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. p. <hi>10</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>THE FORME OF PROFESSION.</hi> p. <hi>15</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the quality of their habits and of their garments. p. <hi>16</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the Divine Office. p. <hi>20</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of Abſtinence. p. <hi>24</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of Confeſſion and of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: of the Confeſſour and his companions. p. <hi>26</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Of the obſervance of Cloyſter. p. <hi>29</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Of the election of the Abbeſs, diſcreetes and other officers. p. <hi>34</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:150050:7"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> The manner of keeping Chapter. p. <hi>38</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> Of ſilence and the manner of speaking at the ſpeak-houſe and at the grate. p. <hi>41</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Of the obſervance of poverty, and that the Sisters may not admit of any poſſeſſions, nor have any thing proper. p. <hi>45</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Of the ſick Siſters. p. <hi>49</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Of the manuall works of the Siſters. p. <hi>52</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Of the correction of the faulty. p. <hi>55</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Of the portreſs and entring into the Monastery. p. <hi>57</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Of the Viſitour. p. <hi>64</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>An exhortation for the better obſervance of theſe preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions. p. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What the Religious are oblig'd to, under mortall ſin, by their vowes. p. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150050:8"/>
               <item>The perfections of the Rule. p. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The praiſe of the Rule. p. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three Priviledges, which our holy Father p. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Francis obtained of Allmighty God. p. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three other Priviledges. p. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Seaven other Previledges, for thoſe that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the Rule &amp; dye in the Order. p. <hi>82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certain Indulgences granted to all the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious of the Order of S. Francis. p. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An examin of conſcience, for à Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. p. <hi>86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Twelve great evills, which come by veniall ſins. p. <hi>88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nine wayes by which we participate of the ſins of others. p. <hi>88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Twelve fruits of the B. Sacrament. p. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Twelve Evangelicall counſayles. p. <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Benediction of our Holy Father S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. p. <hi>91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The malediction of our Holy Father S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis. p. <hi>91</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A PLENARIE ABSOLUTION FROM GUILT AND PAINE.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Otherwiſe call'd. p. <hi>92</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>THE ABSOLUTION OF THE CORDE.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150050:8"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BELOVED and DEVOUT READER, tho' this BOOKE, as to the whole, and every part thereof, might reaſonably be judg'd very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venient and uſefull, at lea'ſt for all Poore Clariſſes; yet (as appear's by the TITLE) it is deſig'nd, fitted out, and printed, particulerly by the CARE, and for the VSE, of the ENGLISH POORE CLARES OF AYRE; in the Dioceſs of S. Omers Who ſignally obſerve theyr INSTITUT, and ORDINANCES upon it, in their NATIVE PURITIE, living accordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly, in the TRUE SPIRIT of S. CLARE, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the GOVERNMENT, and DIRECTION of theyr HOLY ORDER, as both RULE and DECLARATIONS preſcribe, Teache and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly recommen'd unto them.</p>
            <closer>Fiat, Fiat.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:150050:9"/>
            <p>Imprimatur actum in Vicariatu Andomarenſi, die <date>tertiâ Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris 1684.</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>De Mandato</hi> B. DE LARRE Secret.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150050:9"/>
            <head>A PIOUS COLLECTION Of ſeverall profitable directions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions fitted for the English POOR CLARES <hi>In order to the better obſervance of their holy INSTITVTE.</hi> Very uſefull and neceſſary for all Religious Perſons both men and woemen.</head>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>A Morning Exercice, on Sunday.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ALL to mind this ſentence: <hi>Haec dies quam fecit Dominus, exultemus &amp; laetemur in eâ.</hi> This is the day that our lord hath made let us rejoyce and be glad in it. Remember your duty and obligation unto Almighty God, being carefull to ſpend the day wholly in his ſervice and prayſe, and particularly this day honour the moſt Bleſſed Trinity, thanking thoſe three divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Perſons for the benefit of our Creation, and for all others beſtowed either upon your ſelf, or any other in the behalfe of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150050:10"/>
               <head>On Munday Morning.</head>
               <p>CAll to mind this ſentence. <hi>Surge, eur jaces pronus in terram.</hi> Ariſe, why lyeſt thou gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veling on the ground. Remember your banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and punishment or ſuffering of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the preſence of Almighty God, and the company of the Angels, and pray that after your death you may be united unto them offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this day to honour them, but eſpecially your good Angel, beſeeching him and all the others to pray for the ſtate of the Holy Church and that we may ſo uſe this our warfare that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death we may reign with them in all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Tueſday Morning.</head>
               <p>CAll to mind this ſentence. <hi>Surge qui dormis, &amp; exurge à mortuis, &amp; illuminabit te Chriſtus.</hi> Ariſe thou that ſleepeſt with the ſleep of death and Chriſt will illuminate thee. Remember that Chriſt and his holy Ghoſpell are the lights of the Church, and endeavour you to follow the ſame better then you have hitherto done: offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this day to honour the holy Apoſtles, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarks and Prophets, beſeeching them to pray for the converſion of all Heathens, Infidells, and for all thoſe that are out of the Catholick faith, particulerly in England.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150050:10"/>
               <head>Wensday Morning.</head>
               <p>CAll to mind this ſentence: <hi>Surge &amp; comede, grandis tibi reſtat via.</hi> Ariſe and eate, thou haſt yet a great way to go. Think how farr you are from vertue and the perfection of your holy Foundreſſ and Saints of your Order and pray them that they will obtain you ſtrength and force to follow their examples with greater fervour then you have hitherto done, offering this day wholy to their honour, beſeeching them to pray for the good and reformation of the whole Order, and for all Holy Orders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Thursday Morning.</head>
               <p>CAll to mind this ſentence. <hi>Surgite quid dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſurgite &amp; orate ne intretis in tentationem.</hi> Ariſe why do you ſleep. Ariſe and pray leaſt you enter into temptation. Conſider what oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion you give your ſelf to enter into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in negligently employing your time, and being ſlothfull and dull in holy prayer and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Exerciſes, offering this day in honour of the Confeſſours, beſeeching them to obtain for you new fervour of ſpirit and conſtancy in the ſervice of Almighty God, and to pray for the comfort and releaſement of the ſouls in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150050:11"/>
               <head>Friday Morning.</head>
               <p>CAll to mind this ſentence. <hi>Surge, propera a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica mea &amp; veni.</hi> Ariſe, make haſt my beloved and come. Think that our ſweet ſaviour calleth you to ſhew you what he hath ſuffered for you, out of the great love he beareth you. Deſire gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for the ſame. Reſolve that you will with patience ſuffer all ſuch temptations and contempts as it shall pleaſe him to ſend you: And offer this day wholy in honour and memory of his bitter Death and Paſſion, the ſorrowes of his holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and beg the ſuffrages of all the holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs beſeeching them to pray for all thoſe who are in any affliction, or deſolation be it corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or ſpirituall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Saturday Morning.</head>
               <p>CAll to mind this ſentence. <hi>Surge, redde quod debes.</hi> Ariſe &amp; render what thou oweſt. Think what you owe unto Almighty God by the vowes of Poverty, Chaſtity, and obedience, and what you do not pay in this world you muſt ſatisfy in the next. Wherfore offer your ſelf this day wholy to honour the moſt glorious Virgin Mary with all the other Virgins beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them to obtaine grace that you may be more diligent in the obſervance of your vocation, and alſo to pray for the comfort and conſtancy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150050:11"/> of all the Catholicks in England, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your riſing till you go to the work-houſe.</head>
               <p>HAving ſaid one of the foreſaid ſentences that befitteth the day; you muſt riſe with all ſpeed offering your intention according to the ſame and immediatly being riſen, kneel down, and Kiſs the ground with an Elevation of heart unto Almighty God, giving him thanks for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving preſerved you that night, and brought you unto the beginning of the day beſeeching him you may employ it in his ſervice.</p>
               <p>In dreſſing your ſelf ſay theſe ſentences follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing as they are ſet donn.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>In putting on the Habit, ſay.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>INduat me Dominus novum hominem qui ſecundùm Deum creatus eſt in juſtitia &amp; ſanctitate veritatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord cloathe me with the new man, who according to God is created in juſtice, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>In putting on the cord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CIngat me Dominus Ieſus cingulo fortitudinis, ut vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riliter perſeverem in Dei ſervitio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord gird me with the girdle of fortitude &amp; ſtrength, that I may perſever couragiouſly and with alacrity in thy holy ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150050:12"/>
               <head>In putting on the Scapular.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POnat Dominus in corde meo jugum in memoriam Paſsionis &amp; Sanguinis ejus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Lord lay his yoke on my heart as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall of his Paſſion and blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>In waſhing your hands or face.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AMplius lava me Domine ab iniquitate mea, &amp; à peccato meo munda me, meritis Domini nostri IESV CHRISTI filii tui qui dilexit nos, &amp; lavit nos à peccatis nostris in ſanguine ſuo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wash me O Lord yet more from my iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and from my ſin make me cleane through the merits of JESUS CHRIST thy only ſon, who hath loved us and waſhed us with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>In putting on the Cloake.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COoperiat me Dominus IESVS clamyde munditiae &amp; caſtitatis, ut nullum praeter Ieſum amatorem admittam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cover me, O Lord, with the mantle of clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and chaſtity that I may admit of no other lover then my ſaviour JESUS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>In putting on the Kercher.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TEgat me Dominus tegumento paenitentiae contra in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidias Diaboli, ut non praevaleat inimicus contrà me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150050:12"/>
               <p>Cover me, O Lord, in the ſhrowd of Pennan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce againſt the ſnares of the Divell, that my enemy may not prevaile againſt me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>In putting on the veyle.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ACcipiam velamen ſacrum quod ſeram uſque ad. Tribunal aeterni Iudicis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui omnia flectun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur genua: recordabor meipſam, mundum, &amp; ſpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſse &amp; penitus reliquiſſe, ac in veritate me Domino Ieſu ſubjeciſſe, eique tamquàm ſponſo me conjunxiſſe. Ille contrà adverſa omnia me defendat, &amp; ſecum in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam aeternam recipiat. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will put on the ſacred veyle, which I shall appeare in before the Tribunall of the Eternall Judge, to whom all knees do bow. I will call to mind, that I have deſpiſed, &amp; forſaken both the world and my ſelf, to be ſubject in reall truth to my Lord JESUS-CHRIST, and to joyne my ſelf unto him as to my ſpouſe. May he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me in all adverſities, and receive me to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into life everlaſting. AMEN.</p>
               <p>After: or, in ſaying each one of theſe ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces reflect either on your intention in directing your works that day. Or, conſider how great a benefit Almighty God hath beſtowed on you in giving you that day to ſpend in his ſervice, wherby you may glorify his divine Majeſty, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your own merit, and ſatisfy for your ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligences paſt. Call to mind what the ſouls in Purgatory and thouſands in the world would do
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150050:13"/> if they had the ſame means: and alſo think that it may be the laſt day that shall be granted you In this life.</p>
               <p>Being dreſt, make haſt unto the Quire, with out forrein cogitations, recollecting your ſelf, and keeping diligently your ſight, and at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into the Church, after the ſaying. <hi>Aſperges me &amp;c. Thou shalt ſprinkle me</hi> &amp;c. In the taking of holy water. Say, <hi>Domine in multitudine miſericordiae tuae introibo in domum tuam, adorabo ad templum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum tuum in timore tuo.</hi> Lord in the multitude of thy mercy I will enter into thy houſe: in thy feare will I adore thee in thy holy Temple: and kneeling downe at the Perentory ſay. <hi>Adoramus te ſanctiſsime Domine Ieſu Chriſte, hic &amp; ad omnes Ecele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias tuas &amp; benedicimus tibi, quia per ſanctam Crucem tuam redemiſti mundum.</hi> We adore thee o moſt holy Lord JESUS CHRIST, here, and in all thy Churches, and we bleſs thee, becauſe by thy holy Croſs thou haſt redeemed the world.</p>
               <p>After, being in your place, or before the B. Sacrament, imagin Almighty God preſent, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he is, and adore him with the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and humility you can, repreſenting unto your ſelf his Majeſty, Power, and Goodneſs. Accuſtome your ſelf to this in all your Examins, eſpecially that of the morning, noon, and night: and as much as you can in whatſoever exerciſe you undertake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150050:13"/>
               <head>A Morning purpoſe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt: give thanks unto Almighty God for having preſerved you that night, and delivered you from ſo many misfortunes both ſpirituall and corporall which ſince your going to bed thouſands have fallen into.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Examin your conſcience, and ſee wherein you have offended that night, and if you find any thing, humbly crave pardon, begin by Gods grace to amend, and to ſpend the day wholy in his ſervice.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> Offer your ſelf in all that you are, or may be able to perform by your corporall forces or ſpirituall powers unto Almighty God, eſpecially that which you shall do that day with the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for which you offer your actions, in union of the life, death, and Paſſion of our bleſſed ſaviour Chriſt Jesus, the merits of his moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Mother, beſeeching his divine goodnes to diſpoſe wholy and entirely of you, as may be moſt to his honour, and the good of your ſoule in confidence of which reſolve and endeavour to receive all things that day from his holy hands with equall indifference, beholding them as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from his fatherly hands and providence, and the love with which he ſendeth them.</p>
               <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Make a renunciation of your proper will paſſions, and wicked inclinations, or what ſoever may hinder you in the way of perfection and true conformity to the divine will.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150050:14"/>5<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Call to mind what your Obediences ar like to be, and with whom you are to converſe and how you ought to carry your ſelf for the gaining of vertue and overcoming of imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but particularly bend your ſpirituall forces againſt that vice which you find moſt to hinder you, and that you are moſt apt to fall into, purpoſing and reſolving on ſuch means as when the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion preſenteth it ſelf, you may by the grace of God overcome it, calling to mind at that preſent your good purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Offer theſe your good deſires unto Almighty God acknowledging that without his grace you could not have made them, confeſſing your own weakneſs, and force of your externall and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall enemies. Wherfore earneſtly and humbly beg his aſſiſtance by the interceſſion of his holy and bleſſed Mother, whoſe help inſtantly crave, as alſo the aide of your good Angell, with the Saints you are moſt devoted unto, and if you have leiſure ſay the prayers following. <hi>O Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na mea &amp;c.</hi> O my lady, &amp;c. as in the Primer. The oblation of the 7. Aves. with this Prayer unto your Angel Cuſtos.</p>
               <p>O moſt loving Angel, my Gardian, Tutour, Maiſter, Guide, Governour, and defender, wiſe Counſelour, and my moſt faithfull friend, to whom J am commended by the goodnes of God our ſweet Saviour from the inſtant of my birth unto the laſt period of my life: What reverence do J ow you, knowing that you are preſent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150050:14"/> with me? And with what devotion ought J to ſerve you in reſpect of the great care you have of me? And what confidence ougt J to have, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you at my ſide in all occaſions to defend me. Teach me then, O holy Angel: chaſtiſe me, conſerve, and conduct me the right and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red way unto the heavenly Jeruſalem without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting me to do any thing in your preſence which may be offenſive in your ſight, and which J da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re not undertake before another without shame. J beſeech you preſent unto our Lord my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and wants, &amp; obtain me a remedy of his infinit goodnes. Watch when J ſleep, and be not wearied when J am tired: ſtay me when J am ready to fall: raiſe me up when J am fallen, direct me when J am gon aſtray: fortify me when J am weak: illuminate me when J am aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: check the rage of my ſuttle enemie, and at the houre of my death defend me from the infernal dragon, that being guided and aſſiſted by thee J may arrive unto the glorious dwelling place, and thou rejoyce in my good, and J in thy glory, &amp; our Lord King of all glory be honored in us world without end. Amen.</p>
               <p>Theſe Prayers being ended prepare your ſelf to Prime according as it is ſet down in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the Divine Office, being carefull to carry your ſelf with all fervour and devotion, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving well your thoughts: conſidering that you are not only in the preſence of Almighty God, but alſo exerciſing the office of Angels in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150050:15"/> his holy prayſes. Having done this; exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe your ſelf as you have been taught untill it ring to Maſſ, and be carefull to obſerve this manner in all other houres. When the <hi>Litanies</hi> are read do not ſit fiddling with your fingers, turning the leafes of your book, or looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, but imagin you are a poor beggar full of miſeries, afflictions and neceſſities, and that for your greate unworthines to preſent your ſelf before the divine Majeſty of God, you beg an almes through the interceſſion of his Angels and Saints, conſidering that one of them alone is able to ſtrike down infinit men. Likewiſe you are not only to pray for your ſelf, but alſo our Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, and our poor Country: wherfore endeavour to read them with great devotion, and when they are finished make a short examin as you did after Maſſ: and prepare your ſelf to go to <hi>Sext:</hi> In the reading of which, exerciſe your ſelf in the way to Jeruſalem, obſerving the ſame directions: which where ſet down for <hi>Prime.</hi> When Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce is ended make your Examin again, and when the ſigne is given read the <hi>Pater noster</hi> with great devotion and attention for the Benefactours, which being done the ſign will be given to go forth of the Church: then obſerve that modeſty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence which you have been taught. At the firſt entrance being in your cell kneel down, and Kiſſ the ground, offering your little work of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of making your bed unto Almighty God, and exerciſe your ſelf in the way to Jeruſalem
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150050:15"/> untill it ring to the Work-houſe, and rhen take a point therein which is ordained for that time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>From the work-houſe till dinner.</head>
               <p>BEing come unto the Work-houſe and <hi>Veni Creator,</hi> being ſaid, Prepare your ſelf to read the dirge with all devotion and attention. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in what great neceſſity the ſoules in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory are, what paines they ſuffer, and that if you be diligent in praying for them, you may be a means to releaſe tnem: Almighty God having perhaps ordained you for that end: but if you be unmindfull and negligent in the performance thereof, they may be detained from his divine preſence through your fault, and alſo he will permit others when you are in the like caſe to forget you, and neglect to aſſiſt you: wherfore endeavour to be very attentive, and devoutly recollected in reading. After the Dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, the beads are read, unto which give great attention, and read them with devotion: the reſt of your time in the Work-houſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your ſelf in the way to Jeruſalem, carryng your ſelf with all modeſty &amp; ſtill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. When, it ringeth to the ſecond Maſs. <hi>(Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num magni Regis eſt)</hi> (Tis a ſigne that a great King is at hand) being come into the Churh of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer your ſelf unto Almighty God, &amp; make ſome reflexion on your Exerciſe &amp; carriage in the workhouſe. In time of the 2. Maſs Exerciſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150050:16"/> your own devotions. When you go to None obſerve the directions which were ſet down for <hi>Prime</hi> exerciſing your ſelf in the way to Jeruſalem. <hi>None</hi> being read make your Examin how you have ſpent your whole forenoon: for better doing of which crave the aſſiſtance of our ſweet ſaviour, begging pardon where you have failed, and make new reſolutions for the performance of what you purpoſed in the morning, and the exerciſing vertue in all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. After which conſider that it is a punis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hment due to ſin that you muſt now leave the bread of Angels which is holy meditation and Prayer to feed vpon corporall meats: which pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment is due unto the children of Adam: wherfore humbly ſubmit your ſelf unto it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the great hunger, which the poore ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in Purgatory do ſuſtain in being deprived of the preſence of Almightly God, and with hearty compaſſion and great devotion read the <hi>De profundis</hi> for them. Going down, with Grace uſe what is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in the way to Jeruſalem. When you ſit down at the table you may behold our B. Saviour according to that foreſaid exerciſe, who lived in this world 33. years, and humbly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſelf unto all pennances due unto men for their ſins: wherfore beg grace to uſe this Corporall food, becauſe it tis his bleſſed will and give your body its neceſſities, not uſing the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein ſuperfluitie to pleaſe nature or ſenſualit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: but ſeaſon your meat in the wounds of our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150050:16"/> B. Saviour: and drink from the delicious foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of his ſacred ſide, mingled with the gall and vinegar which he drank for your ſake, Being at dinner give your attention wholy to that which is read at the table. At twelve of the clock exerciſe that which is appointed in the way to Jeruſalem, ſaying. <hi>Chriſtus factus est pro nobis obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens:</hi> after which you may return to that which is read at the table. When you have dined, make ſome little reflexion how you have behaved your ſelf: if you find to have fallen, humbly crave pardon, purpoſing to amend. At the going up, with Grace exerciſe your ſelf in the way to Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p>From Dinner untill the Examen at night. When Grace is finished read your Pater noſters for your benefactours; When you come to your Cell you may ſtay there untill it ring to the work-houſe, employing your ſelf in reading wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or keeping your devotion, or doing ſome other thing which you deſir. When the Bell calleth you to work, exerciſe your ſelf there according to the ſame directions, which are ſet down for the forenoon, uſing the Way to Jeruſalem, After your beads are read untill it ring to Evenſong. And then leave your work ſaying. <hi>Hoc ſignum &amp;c.</hi> And making what haſt you can into the Church, being kneeled down either in your place, or els<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, make your short Examin; which being don read the little office, if you have not read it before, Keeping your Devotion untill it ring up to Evenſong: in the reading of which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150050:17"/> obſerve well your thoughts, and the manner which was ſet down from <hi>Prime.</hi> The Office being ended prepare your ſelf to Meditation, and afterwads the ſigne being given, make your short Examen, as it is ſet down in the directions for mentall prayer. When you go forth of the Church, employ your ſelf in the way to Jeruſalem untill you go to Collation, where when you have ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in conſidering the Myſtery of the Washing of the feet give your attention to that which is read at the Table<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when you have ended Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, you may read that which you meane to make your Meditation of, if you have not read it before, or do not take that which is read at the table: being-ſure never to omit the matter before Meditation. The beſt time to read it is the quarter before five<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when the ſigne is given after Meditation, going up from Collation uſe the way to Jeruſalem, and continue the ſame untill Recollection: then kneeling in your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, make your Examen: Firſt, preſent Your ſelf before Almighty God and give him thanks for all the benefits you have received that day: in particular eſteeming your ſelf as unworthy of them as any creature on earth, or the ſoules in Hell: as alſo the miſeries both ſpirituall and temporall, from which he hath delivered you, to be as many and as great as are, or might have fallen upon any in the world.</p>
               <p>Secondly, beg grace to ſee the offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that day acknowledging your unableneſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150050:17"/> to do the ſame without his ſpeciall aſſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Thirdly: how you have ſpent that day with obedience, and exerciſes you have had, weighing wherein you have failed by omiſſion or commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in thought, word, or work, towards Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, your ſiſters and your ſelf: how you have exerciſed your interiour powers, your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, particularly your ſight, and eſpecially how you have obſerved the ſervices and exerciſes of your Religion, whether you have governed your exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour with that modeſty, mortification, ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and mildnes, that you are taught.</p>
               <p>Fourthly: if you ſee your ſelf to have overco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me any imperfection, give thanks unto Almighty God, and where you find to have failed and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, humbly crave pardon.</p>
               <p>Fiftly: purpoſe with his holy grace to be more carefull and watchfull over your ſelf the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, making ſuch reſolutions as may help you moſt for the overcoming of that vice wherein you find your ſelf that day to have ſinned in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Then ſay the Prayer following.</head>
               <p>I Confeſs unto you, O Lord God omnipotent Creatour of heaven and earth, all my ſins which ever I have committed even from my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy untill this preſent-houre wittingly or ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly, and particularly this day in thought word, or work. To you, O Lord only I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my offences and beg pardon for them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150050:18"/> as being innumerable: therfore I humbly beſeech thee to forgive and forget all, whereof thou kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt me guilty in all my life paſt, and enkindle in me a fervent amendment with faith, hope, and charity, O mercifull, O pittifull o ſweet JESUS ſonne of the B. Virgin Mary.</p>
               <p>Going to your cell make uſe of that which is ordained in the way to Jeruſalem, and during that time you are undreſſing your ſelf, call to mind the ſtrict account, which you are to render unto Almighty God when the day of this life is ended: alſo of the uncertaintie to live untill the next morning, much leſs any longer, reflecting how many miſeries may and will fall upon thouſands before your upriſing: and alwaies before you go to bed kneeling commend your ſelf to our ſweet ſaviour, and his bleſſed Mother with your good Angell, Kiſſing the ground and the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix. Being laid in bed, think you lay your mouth to the ſacred ſide or feet of or ſweet Saviour, ſaying the prayer following.</p>
               <p>O moſt ſweet Lord JESUS CHRIST in union of the love which cauſed thee to create for us this corporall reſt, and diſdainedſt not thy ſelf to take the ſame whilſt thou livedſt here on earth: I do make uſe of the ſame to fulfill the neceſſity of my body, that it may be more prompt and ready to ſerve thee. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150050:18"/>
               <head>Before ſleeping ſay thus.</head>
               <p>O Moſt ſweet JESUS let me now reſt upon thy ſacred breaſt, and grant me to fetch my breath out of thy moſt ſacred heart, that thy ſweet ſpirit may flow into my ſoul, vivificate my mind and vnſeparably unite me unto thee ſweet JESUS; ſo often as this night I do fetch my breath, ſo many millions of praiſes I beſeech thee receive from me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Vnto your good Angel ſay.</head>
               <p>O Angell of God who art my keeper, illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, preſerve, rule, and govern me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thy charge by the ſupernall power this night and evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>A direction how to ſay the way to Jeruſalem.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AT five a clock when Meditation is ended, going to put off your cloake, take the Myſtery wherein our ſaviour took leave of his B. Mother.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When it ringeth to Collation, that which is then preſent, his going unto the place where he made his ſupper.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When you are at Collation, the washing of the feet.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150050:19"/>4. That of the Inſtitution of the moſt B. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, the which continue till the end of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Then take our ſaviour's going into the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with his diſciples.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When the B. Sacrament is ſeen, the three prayers which he made in the garden.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Going forth of the Church, his betraying.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In your cell his being at Annas's, and leave him there untill <hi>Matins;</hi> at which time go with him to Caiphas, and find him there at <hi>Prime.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Under which go with him to Pilate, and from thence to Herod.</p>
               <p n="10">10. At <hi>Terce</hi> take the Myſtery of the white garment.</p>
               <p n="11">11. At <hi>Sext</hi> the whipping and crowning with thorns, Going forth of the Church, our ſaviour's being lead and shewed to the people.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Making your bed, remember the three ſentences of death which were given againſt him.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Going to the Workhouſe his going with his Croſs to be crucified, and paſſing through the golden gate.</p>
               <p n="14">14. In the workhouſe the three falls: the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of our ſweet ſaviour with his holy Mother, Simon Cyrenean, &amp; Veronica.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Going forth from the Workhouſe, the carrying the Croſs up Mount Calvary.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Between the two peales to <hi>None,</hi> his ſitting naked upon the ſtone.</p>
               <p n="17">17. At <hi>None,</hi> the nailing to the Croſs.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150050:19"/>18. Going down to Grace, how the Croſs was reared up and ſet in the place where it was to ſtand.</p>
               <p n="19">19. At twelve a clock behold our ſaviour hanging on high upon the Croſs, ſaying theſe firſt words, <hi>Father forgive them for they know not what they do.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. From <hi>evenſong,</hi> exerciſe your ſelf in the 7. words: the piercing of our Saviours ſide: his taking down from the Croſſ, and lyng in the lap of his Mother, his buriall, and deſcending into Limbo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>How to apply the ſeaven Words.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>FAther forgive them for they know not what they do.</hi> Here pray for all thoſe that are in mortall ſin: for all Heathens, and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and beſeech Almighty God to illuminate their hearts, and pardon their offences.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>This day thou shalt be with me in Paradiſe.</hi> Pray for the happy departure of all faithfull Chriſtians, and releaſement of the ſoules in Purgatorie.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Son behold thy Mother:</hi> and again, <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man behold thy ſon.</hi> Recommend to our B. Lady your ſelf, your Parents, kinred and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours and the ſtate of the whole church: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching our ſweet Saviour to give her unto us for Patroneſſ, Mother, and Advocate, and grant us grace to ſerve, honour, and obey her.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150050:20"/>4. <hi>I thirſt.</hi> Pray that wee, and all creatures may continually thirſt after juſtice and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</hi> Here pray for the comfort and aſſiſtance of all in temptation or affliction, either ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or corporall.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>It is conſummated.</hi> Beſeech Almighty God that his holy will may be accomplished in you, and all creatures to the perfect praiſe of his moſt holy name.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Father, into thy hands I commend my ſpirit.</hi> Pray rhat as he recommended his to his heavenly Father, our ſoules may be protected by him in this life by the fruition of his holy grace, and in the next received to that beatitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de which by his death and Paſſion he ha's purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>The <hi>7.</hi> Ave's which are to be read for the <hi>7.</hi> ſorrowes of or B. Lady; you may take according to your devotion, or theſe following.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe departure of our ſweet Saviour when he went to make his laſt ſupper.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When S. John brought her word of our Saviours being apprehended, and his cruell uſage.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When shee mett him bearing his Croſſ.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When shee beheld him crucified upon the Croſſ.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150050:20"/>5. The cruell piercing of his ſacred ſide.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When shee had him dead in her lap.</p>
               <p n="7">7. When shee parted from the body of her deare ſon at his buriall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Conſiderations on the <hi>3. Pater noſters,</hi> and <hi>Aves</hi> which are ſaid at the shewing of the B. Sacrament: in honour of the Prayer in the Garden, offering your intention to gain the Pardon.</head>
               <p n="1">1. SAy the firſt <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Ave,</hi> in honour of the unſpeakable love with which our ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour made oblation of his dolorous agony, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by the merits of the ſame, that our ſins may be forgiven us, and that we be reconciled to his heavenly Father, and obtain ſtrength and comfort in our temptations and afflictions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The 2. <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Ave,</hi> in honour of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire reſignation with which our B. Saviour offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Prayer: crave therby grace to conform our ſelves unto the divine will, and attain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect union with Almighty God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The 3. <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Ave,</hi> ſay in honour of our ſweet Saviours perſeverance in his moſt painfull prayer, beſeeching him that by the merits of the ſame wee may not leave of the good once begun for the repugnance wee feel, or want of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein, but with love and confidence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſever to the end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150050:21"/>
               <head>After your Examin at night, you may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute our B. Lady with theſe <hi>3 Ave's.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. BY the firſt beſeech her that she will obtain for you pardon of all your ſins, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe you have committed that day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That shee will pleaſe to preſent all your works unto her bleſſed ſon, rendring them agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by her merits in whatſoever is wanting on their part.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Recommend your ſelf unto her, and beſeech her that shee will preſerve you from all ſin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits and illuſious of the divell, and particularly from all evills.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>How to ſay your <hi>Pater noſter's</hi> and <hi>Ave's</hi> in thanksgiving unto Almighty God for his benefits either for night or any other time.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe firſt <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Ave</hi> addreſſ to the right hand of our ſweet Redeemer offering to his Eternall Father, the precious blood which iſſued out of his moſt ſacred wound in thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for the benefit of your Creation and the Creation of all others, as alſo of all things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for mans uſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The 2. addreſſ unto the ſacred wound of his left hand in thanks giving for the benefit of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150050:21"/> conſetving you from evils, and the like for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The 3. addreſſ unto the wound of his right foot in thanksgiving for the benefit of your Redemption, and the like for others.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The 4. addreſſ unto the ſacred wound of his left foot in thanksgiving for the benefit of your vocation, and all others on whom he hath beſtowed the like.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The 5. addreſſ unto the ſacred wound of his bleſſed heart, for all generall and particular benefits, either ſpirituall or corporall, which with ſo great love he hath beſtowed on you, and all creatures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>An Exerciſe for Maſſ.</head>
               <p>FIrſt know that Maſſ is a ſacrifice, wherein is offered the very ſame body and blood of our Saviour, that was before offered upon the Croſſ, and was infinitely able to redeem infinit worlds: and ſith the world is ſufficiently redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with one redemption, he gives unto every one ſuch and ſo great grace, as he hath prepared himſelf to receive: therfore, like as a man that fetcheth water forth of the ſea cannot want for any ſcarcity that is there, yet he may want by reaſon of the littleneſſ of his veſſell: even ſo no man need want grace coming unto this holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice if the veſſell of his heart be of ſufficient bigneſſ. Wherfore prepare your ſelf worthily,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150050:22"/> and beg ſuch grace, devotion, reverence and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, as the worthines of the ſacrifice following requires.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>The Exerciſe.</head>
               <p>THe Prieſt ſignifieth God, the Altar the church: and as the Altar is of many ſtones, ſo is the church of God, of many people. Wherfore you muſt not heare Maſſ for your ſelf alone, but for the whole church: for ſince he is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lord, he is not delighted with particular ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before Maſſ.</head>
               <p>O Good JESUS vouchſafe me the vertue of your holy grace, and grant J beſeech you that J may purely aſſiſt at this divine ſacrifice of the holy Maſſ to the eternall praiſe of your holy name in memory of all that you have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſuffer for my ſake, and for all mankind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>When the Prieſt ſaith the <hi>Confiteor.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſider the offences of our firſt parents with thoſe of the whole world, and in particular thoſe which you have your ſelf committed, and at the <hi>Kyrie elerſon,</hi> aske moſt humbly pardon for them, and beg grace for amendment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:150050:22"/>
               <head>At Gloria in excelſis.</head>
               <p>COnſider how the Angels in heaven rejoyce at the converſion of a ſinner, wherfore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech them through the great deſire they have of mans ſalvation to aid and aſſiſt us, and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to obtain the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the Epiſtle.</head>
               <p>COnſider that this World is a place of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and be ſorry that ſo few do embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce the ſame, but follow vain pleaſures and delights: and beſeech Almighty God to enlighten their hearts, and offer your ſelf to ſuffer whatſoever it shall pleaſe him to lay upon you, begging grace for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the Ghospell.</head>
               <p>COnſider what pains our Saviour took in this world going from one place to another, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and inviting all men to follow his moſt perfect example and doctrin, begging by the merits of his pains and labours, that you may be a true follower thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the Creed.</head>
               <p>THink what a multitude of people were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the holy Ghoſpell; and nevertheleſſ
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150050:23"/> how many there are which remain in blindnes, and wil not be lightned, for which be heartily ſorry, and beſeech God to convert them, but principally pray for the converſion of England.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the Offertory.</head>
               <p>COnſider the promptitude with which our ſweet Saviour offered himſelf into the hands of his heavenly Fathet to ſuffer his bitter death and Paſſion for your Redemption, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. Wherfore offer your ſelf wholly to his divine goodneſſ with your vowes of obedience, Poverty, and Chaſtity, purpoſing from thence forward to be crucified by theſe three nailes to the Croſſ of all mortification.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the Preface.</head>
               <p>COnſider how our ſweet Saviour raiſed La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus after he had been dead four daies: and thence you may draw comfort and confidence, that although you find many evil cuſtomes in your ſelf, all hindering you from the true ſervice of God: yet acknowledge that he is able to rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and deliver you from them all. Wherfore you muſt purpoſe ſtrongly to reſiſt them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the grace and ſtrength, which it shall pleaſe him to give you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150050:23"/>
               <head>At Sanctus.</head>
               <p>COnſider how the Angels in heaven do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually praiſe Almighty God, and how pleaſing their ſervice is unto him: wherfore pray unto them to obtain for you ſuch fervour of ſpirit in this life that at your death you may be worthy to be aſſiſted by them in heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the Canon.</head>
               <p>COnſider the unſpeakable love of our Saviour in offering himſelf for you in this moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sactifice: weighing his Majeſties greatnes and Omnipotency, which is therein contained: and here you may pray for the intention of the whole church, and for all thoſe you are to pray for that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer at the Elevation of the moſt B. Hoſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ADoro te Domine Ieſu Christe &amp; benedico tibi, qui pro nobis in cruce moriens redemiſti mundum. Ave caro Chriſti immaculata Crucis hoſtia, morte tuâ nos a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marâ fac redemptos luce clarâ tecum frui gloriâ. Deus propitius eſto mihi peccatori. Aufer à me quicquid tibi diſplicet. Infunde in me quicquid tibi placet. Converte me totum tuum dulcis Ieſu, Deus meus. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J adore thee o Lord JESUS CHRIST, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150050:24"/> J bleſſ thee who dying on the Croſſ for us, haſt redeemed the world. Haile holy flesh of CHRIST, immaculate hoſt of the Croſſ, Make us, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by thy bitter death, to enjoy with thee in glory, eternall light. God be mercifull to me a ſinner. Take away from me all that is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to thee; infuſe into me all that is pleaſing to thee. Convert me wholy to thee ſweet JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS my God. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer at the Elevation of the Chalice.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAnguis tuus Domine Ieſu Chriſte pro nobis effuſus, ſit nobis in remiſsionem omnium peccatorum noſtrorum, negligentiarum, &amp; ignorantiarum noſtrarum: in robur &amp; augmentum fidei, ſpei, charitatis, gratiarum, &amp; vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum: in cautelam vitae, in adoptionem gloriae aeternae in abſolutionem omnium fidelium defunctorum &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium pro quibus orare tenemur. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let thy blood, O Lord JESUS CHRIST, which was shed for us, be a remiſſion of all our ſins, negligences and ignorances, a ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and encreaſe of faith, hope, charity, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and virtues, a caution to my life, an adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to eternall glory, an abſolution of all the faithfull departed, and of all for whom we are bound to pray. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Whilst the Pater noſter is ſaid.</head>
               <p>COnſider who made this Prayer, and joyne your intention with the Prieſt's, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peateth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150050:24"/> it for the neceſſities of the whole church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>An Excrciſe for the <hi>5.</hi> Pater noſters after the Elevation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt you make a particular intention to get pardon, and to diſpoſe your ſelf to receive the Bleſſed Sacrament, either corporally or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually for the which obſerve this exerciſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt <hi>Pater</hi> and <hi>Ave,</hi> addreſſ to the right hand of our B. Saviour beſeeching him that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious blood which iſſued out of this his ſacred wound may ſerve you for a bath to wash and purify you from all ſtaines and ſpots of your ſins, and particularly thoſe which you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſince your laſt confeſſion.</p>
               <p>The 2. addreſſ to the left hand, beſeeching him that the ſacred blood which iſſued from the ſame may ſerve for a ſpirituall balſome to cure all your infirmities, and ſpirituall ſickneſſes.</p>
               <p>The 3. addreſſ unto the wound of his right foot, beſeeching him by his ſacred blood which iſſued forth thereof, that it will pleaſe him to adorn you with the garment of charity, and purity of heart and mind.</p>
               <p>The 4. addreſſ to his left foot, beſeeching him that his ſacred blood which iſſued forth of this wound may lighten the eyes of the ſoule to know his greatnes, feare his juſtice, and love his goodnes.</p>
               <p>The 5. addreſſ unto the ſacred blood which iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued from thence that he will pardon and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150050:25"/> all your inordinate deſires and affections and unite your heart to his through perpetuall love and continuall memorie of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before ſpirituall Communion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Pie Domine Ieſu Christe, qui huc propter me ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſti, &amp; te mihi in panem quotidiaenum, imo in omnem deſiderabilem uſum tribuiſti; vellem te libenter etiaem in Sacramento ſuſcipere, ſed heu non audeo, nec poſsum accedere, quia timeo te offendere propter indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem meam inimicam &amp; tamen ſcio quod ſine te vero cibo non poſsum vivere: quare humiliter te rogo ut licèt non ſumam te ſacramentaliter, me tamen reficias &amp; ad me deſcendas ſpiritualiter &amp; velis mihi gratiam imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiri, quam te devotè ſumentes debent ſentire. O bone Ieſu noli me deſpicere, noli me indignam famulam tuam tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; ſed digneris ad me venire, mecum manere, &amp; effectus tuos in me operari. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O moſt pious Lord JESUS CHRIST, who cameſt hither for me, and haſt given thy ſelf to me for my' daily bread, yea to every deſirable uſe. J would willingly receive thee even in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: but alas J dare not, nor can J approach, becauſe J am afraid to offend thee by reaſon of my indiſpoſition offenſive to thy eye: and yet J know that J cannot live without thee the true food: Wherfore J moſt humbly beſeech thee, that altho J do not receive thee Sacramentally, yet that thou wouldſt refresh me, and come down to me ſpiritually, and impart unto me that grace,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150050:25"/> which thoſe that receive thee devoutly muſt feel. O Good JESU deſpiſe me not, and paſſ not by me thy unworthy ſervant, but vouchſafe to come to me, and to remain with me, and work thy effects in me. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>An Exerciſe to be ſaid by word or heart when you Communicate ſpiritually or corporally.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHen the Prieſt ſaith <hi>Domine non ſum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus,</hi> ſay interiourly at the 1. time. O my God J am not worthy for the multitude of my ſins that the earth should beare me.</p>
               <p n="2">2. At the 2. O my God J merit not to lift up my eyes to behold the heavens.</p>
               <p n="3">3. At the 3. O my God, J am she who for my iniquities merit no other then hell; but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, O infinit goodnes, leave not to viſit me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A devout Prayer to be ſaid in time of Communion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Bone</hi> JESU, <hi>dilecte mi, chariſsime mi, amor meus, dulcedo cordis mei, vita animae meae. O ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum bonum meum, melliflue</hi> JESU <hi>miſerere mei, uni me tibi intimè ad gloriam nominis tui. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O good JESU, my beloved my deareſt, my love, the ſweetneſſ of my heart, the life of my ſoule. O my Eternall good, mellifluous JESU
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150050:26"/> have pitty on me, unite me to thy ſelf moſt intimately, to the glory of thy name. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>O Light increated, illuminate my darkneſſ, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate my underſtanding with pure know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, replenish my memory with holy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and chaſt thoughts, ſet my will on fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re with a holy and enflamed love, quicken my ſoule and make that J may taſt the vertue of your holy preſence, and by the ſame ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in me, and let me remain in you. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Thanksgiving after you Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated ſpiritually or Corporally.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRatias tibi ago Domine</hi> JESU CHRISTE, <hi>qui me tantis Sacramentis ſpiritualibus refecisti; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge Domine obſecro reverentiam, mane mecum per gratiam, &amp; fac me hodie &amp; ſemper tuis obedire man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis, ut effectus &amp; virtutes hujus Sacramenti ſentiam. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J give thee thanks. O Lord JESU CHRIST, who haſt refresht me with ſuch great ſpirituall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments: grant me, J beſeech you, reverence; ſtay with me by your grace, and make me this day, &amp; alwayes obedient to your commands, that J may feel the effects and vertues of this Sacrament. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:150050:26"/>
               <head>When the Prieſt ſayes Agnus Dei.</head>
               <p>COnſider how your ſweet ſaviour is rhe lamb of God who hath offered himſelf for all the ſins of the world, and is now at the right hand of his Father to be the Advocate and Judge of ſinners. Pray him humbly to pardon you your offences, and make you worthy ſpiritually to receive him, which indeavour to do with the Prieſt in the devouteſt manner you can, and with the greateſt affection you are able.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>When the Priest ſaith the last Collect or Prayer.</head>
               <p>GIve thanks unto the holy Trinity for having granted you ſo great a benefit as to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and prataker of ſo worthy a Myſtery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the laſt Dominus Vobiſcum.</head>
               <p>IMagin as if you heard the ſound of the Angels trumpet, wherwith our Lord at the end of the world will call to Judgment, and beſeech him to give you grace to be ready and prepared againſt that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>When the Prieſt ſaith Ite Miſsa est.</head>
               <p>COnſider that at the laſt day of Judgment the wicked shall be condemned to everlaſting
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150050:27"/> pain and torment, and perpetually deprived of the preſence of Almighty God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>At the last Benediction.</head>
               <p>COnſider the Benediction which Almighty God will give to all the Elect, and will lead them unto everlaſting reſt: wherfore beſeech him ſo to bleſs you and all creatures both in this life and in the next as you and all other may perpetually bleſs his holy Name. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>At the End of Maſs, ſay the Prayer following.</head>
               <p>SWeet JESUS I offer unto thee the ſacrifice of this holy Maſs, and of all the Maſſes which shall be ſaid throughout the whole world, by means whereof I beſeech you to give me know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of my ſins and miſeries, as alſo to reſtore the ruins and defects of my poor ſoule, and to ſupply my wants and unworthineſs: mortify in me whatſoever is diſpleaſing unto your divine Majeſty and make me one according to your own heart: conform my ſpirit, ſoul, and body to that of your ſacred humanity, and alwayes il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate and direct me by the ſight of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Divinitie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſaid this Prayer under the Ghoſpell Examin how you have behaved your ſelf in this holy Myſtery, and if you find your ſelf to have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150050:27"/> failed humbly crave pardon of Almighty God, purpoſing by his holy grace to amend, &amp; be more diligent the next day. DEO GRATIAS.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Certain intentions or Meditations which we ought to have when we Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate: out of S. Bonav.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt to unite our ſelves more &amp; more to Almighty God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To gain therby ſome vertue or grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To acknowledge his benefits which we cannot do in any thing which is more pleaſing and agreable to him then by worthily frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The deſire of the praiſe of Almighty God, and his goodneſs, the ſame being a Sacrifice of praiſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To receive the ſpirit of Chriſt Jeſus, &amp; to live in humility, charity, Obedience, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of ſpirit, mortification of body, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, that thy Redeemer may live in thee, who is thy finall end.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To renew the memory of the Paſſion of Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Conſiderations before Communion taken out of the ſame Saint.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE are to meditate vhat we are about to do; which is to receive Chriſt Jeſus,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150050:28"/> true God and true man, who died upon the Croſs for us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That we are to receive the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: for which cauſe, it behoveth that we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach thereunto, without ſin; purging our ſelves by true Contrition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider the divine Excellency and our own miſery: how great this Lord is, and how meane the ſervant. Ponder that his goodneſs is much more then our offences, or vertues.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Stirr up in your ſelf a moſt fervent deſire to harbour in your heart ſuch a loving Lord: The holy Doctour ſaith it is a very ſtrange thing that man receiving into his ſoule Almighty God in the moſt B. Sacrament, his heart does not even faint, yea even burſt through vehemency of love.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Fooure conſiderations of S. Mathildis before Communion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe great love of God who had remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of her from all Eternity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he created her Knowing how ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull shee would be unto his divine Majeſty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That he would dy for her, upon the Croſs, and with his ſacred blood ſatisfy his Eternall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for her demerits.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That for her love he would remain in the holy Sacrament to feed her with his own bleſſed body and Cleanſe her with his owne ſacred blood.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150050:28"/>
               <head>A Prayer before receiving the B. Sacrament.</head>
               <p>O Sweet JESUS J moſt ardently deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you Sacramentally and ſpiritually: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though J know my ſelf to be moſt unworthy you should enter into the houſe of my ſoule; be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorable unto me wretched ſinner, and take from me whatſoever is diſpleaſing unto you: prepare in me, and in all hearts a habitation agreable unto your divine Majeſty. Would to God, O my ſweet Saviour JESU, would to God J were wholy enflamed with an ardent deſire and love of you. Behold J here renounce, and give up to you all things, O ſweet JESU, O JESU, my love for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer after receiving the B. Sacrament.</head>
               <p>O Moſt ſweet Lord JESUS CHRIST, J hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thy unspeakable mercy, that this holy Sacrament of thy pretious body and blood which J unworthy have received, may be to me and to all ſinners a full purgation of all our offences, a ſtrength againſt frailties, a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſ to defend us againſt all perills both of ſoul and body, an entire pardon and eſtablishment in all grace, an amendment of life, a continuall memoriall of thy ſacred Paſſion, a nourishment againſt all ſpirituall weakneſs and a ſtaff of our <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150050:29"/> Pilgrimage: let it, my ſweet Saviour JESUS, guide us going, reduce us ſtraying, receive us returning again, hold us up ſtumbling, lift us up falling and perſevering bring us to glory. O higheſt God let the reception of this moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sacrament ſo alter the taſt of our hearts, that at no time we feel any ſweetneſs, love, or deſire, and conſolation, admit any delight, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teem any honour, feare any adverſity, or even-live but for thee, and to accomplish thy bleſſed will, which may ever be perfected in us. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Moſt glorious and ever bleſſed Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, O holy Father S. Francis, O holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther S. Clare, S. Michaël, Angels, Archangells, Vertues, Powers, Principalities, Dominations, Thrones, Cherubins, Seraphins, and all cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall Spirits, J beſeech you to proſtrate before the face of my God, and beſeech him in favour of his moſt deare ſon, my Saviour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer CHRIST JESUS, that it will pleaſe him to pardon the unworthines and indevotion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewith J have received the moſt bleſſed and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall Sacrament, and do not permit the ſame to cauſe that the ſpirit thereof be not communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto me alſo, that by the vertue and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of this holy Communion J may feel the effect of his divinë mercy: that I may receive
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150050:29"/> this day a full remiſſion of all my ſins, true light and knowledge of his grace, which is in me: that be reduce and put me in ſuch an eſtate as shall be moſt pleaſing unto his divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: augment in me faith, hope, charity, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, chaſtity and patience, with all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and gifts of the holy Ghoſt, neceſſary to procure the glory of his divine Majeſty, and the ſalvation of my ſoule to the honour and praiſe of his holy name. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>What we ought to do the day we communicate.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BE very careful to govern our ſences, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially our tongue; and if it happen we fall by frailty, we ought preſently to crave par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and beſeech our ſweet Saviour not therfore to abſent himſelf from us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To render to this bleſſed gueſt all the beſt ſervices we are able, he being infinitely worthy to be ſerved, loved, and adored of all creatures. Wishing above all things his holy honour and pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Seek ſtill to entertain this bleſſed ſpouſe with holy thoughts and deſires, beſeeching him to give you and all others, whatſoever he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be needfull for his love and ſervice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving that he is ineſtimably rich, and a moſt liberal giver.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Do nothing that day without conſidering
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150050:30"/> firſt whether the thing you do will be pleaſing and agreable unto him, and demand his permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and leave.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Make fervent aſpirations, caſt forth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of divine love towards that moſt amiable and ſweet Lord with a vehement deſire of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him infinitely, and be wholy transformed into him by conformity of will. Deo gratias.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before Confeſſion.</head>
               <p>O Soverain Creatour of heaven and earth, and of all things which in them are: J worm and miſerable wretch have offended your divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Majeſty, I wonder at my folly, deteſt my ingratitude, and lament my offences, craving through the merits of the bitter Paſſion and death of your onely begotten ſon, and the infinite love, with which he did both offer and ſuffer them for my ſake, and for the whole world: grant unto me and all ſinners true knowledge and perfect contrition of our ſins and offences with entire remiſſion of them all, looſe us from the chaines of our imperfections, and heale the wounds of our ſoules: grant us ever to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and refreshed in the fountain of his holy wounds. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer after Confeſſion.</head>
               <p>O Good IESU let this my Confeſſion be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull and acceptable unto you by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150050:30"/> of your admirable life and painfull death, with all the labours, anguishes, and ſorrowes, which you ſuffered for mankind, together with thoſe of your B. Mother, and all your holy Saints ſupplying whatſoever is wanting in me, either now or any other time, through want of true contrition, entire confeſſion, or full ſatisfaction: beſeeching they may alſo be unto me light, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and ſtrength in all my wayes unto the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect poſſeſſion of you my ſweet IESU in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Directions how to ſay the Divine Office with due devotion and attention.</head>
               <p>WHat care we ought to have in ſaying the divine Office according to the examples of the holy men, is witten in the 27. Chapter of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralipomenon, <hi>Deſpiſe not your ſelf, our Lord hath choſen you to stand before him and adore him.</hi> Wherfore ſince God hath choſen man to ſo high a prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is very requiſit we should know how, and in what manner humble ſervice doth conſiſt. The holy man Gerſon affirmeth that in ſaying your Mattins and other houres, carefully and ſtudiouſly, leaſurely and diſtinctly, conſiſteth the greateſt exerciſe of a Religious man, and is ſo fit for him as nothing more. S. Benedict doth call this the worke of our Lord, eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it it is the chiefeſt office that any man can perform gratefull to the divine Majeſty. S.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150050:31"/> Jerome doth affirm that to offer up Hymns, Pſalmes, and ſpirituall prayers, and to shed teares for our own offences, and thoſe of our neighbour, is to reconcile the people to God, and to paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy our Lord with his flock: all which things are to be accomplished in the divine office. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought very diligently to apply our whole ſtudy, and inward powers to the due execution thereof: leaſt perhaps that dreadfull ſentence pronounced by the Prophet Jeremy c. 48. v. 10. fall upon us, <hi>maledictus qui facit opus Domini fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenter.</hi> Artursd be be who do's our lords worke negligently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Three ſorts of preparation for ſaying the Divine Offices.</head>
               <p>THe firſt of living well, which is to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in doing all pious works, to reſtrain our ſelves from all vanities, and daily to keep our hearts free and pure from all things that may in the leaſt ſort ſoyle them, alwaies directing our thoughts and works whatſoever unto Almighty God and his honour.</p>
               <p>The 2. is, that before we begin the Divine Office, we be carefull to recollect our ſpirits, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all forrain thoughts, or whatſoever may give us diſtraction in our Divine Office, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſeriouſly what wee are going bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> It behoveth us alſo diligently to weigh theſe, things following.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150050:31"/>
               <p>That we come
<list>
                     <item>To worship God.</item>
                     <item>To thank God.</item>
                     <item>To intreate God.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt we come to <hi>worship God</hi> in three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and one eſſence with the worship of <hi>Patria</hi> which is due to God alone, for the benefit of juſtification, that is the Incarnation of his only ſon, our B. Saviour his life, death, Reſurrection, and Aſcenſion; which Myſteries we ought ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refully to conſider, and ponder with great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and reverence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We come to <hi>thank God</hi> in prayſing him for the great benefits which we have received and do momentarily receive, and hope to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive herafter. Therfore it is requiſit that we behold and renew the ſame every houre and moment of our life: but eſpecially when we are ſo particularly employed in a worke that hath ſo great relation and adherence thereunto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We go to <hi>intreat God,</hi> in beſeeching his moſt immeaſurable clemency for our own ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities and thoſe of the whole Church: but to bring all theſe particulars with more facility to our mind it will aſſiſt us much, attentively to think that nothing is more neceſſary or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for us then God.</p>
               <p>The 3. Preparation is a zealous prayer, which we muſt make to the end we may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily finish the task of our devotions, and in imitation of the three Kings offer to his divine
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150050:32"/> goodnes the <hi>gold</hi> of devotion, the <hi>frankincenſe</hi> of attention, and the <hi>Myrrhe</hi> of conſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance.</p>
               <p>Being to begin the Office you may ſay. I adore thee O Chriſt, and bleſs thee O Lord, for by thy Croſs and Paſſion thou haſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the world. Thou art my God, and I will exalt thee; To thee be praiſe. To thee be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. To thee be thanks giving for ever. All creatures worthily worship thee; praiſe, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, and adore the moſt high and undivided Trinity, and the humanity of my bleſſed Lord Jeſu, who in time paſt was converſant with men upon earth, and now ſits at the right hand of his Eternall Father: J beſeech the Holy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the holy Angels and Saints, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe whoſe feaſts are celebrated this day throug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout the whole Church, that they will all help me with their aid and furtherance, to the end I may finish this my office worthily to the true praiſe of Almighty God, and the profit of my ſoule Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>For the Prayer before the leſſer Houres take either <hi>REX CHRISTE &amp;c.</hi> or the Prayer following.</head>
               <p>O Good Jeſu I deſire for the love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which I owe unto you, humbly to obey you, faithfully to ſerve you, and purely
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150050:32"/> to love you, in union of that moſt perfect at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, which you being here on Earth prayed and praiſed your heavenly Father. Help me O Lord Jeſu with your holy grace, for being left by you, I shall be able to do nothing. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>Devout Meditations at Gloria Patri.</head>
               <p>GLory be to the Father, who when I was not, hath created me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the ſon, who when I was loſt hath redeemed me.</p>
               <p>Glory be to the Holy Ghoſt, who hath ſanctified me, and the elect of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations_for_the_hours">
               <p>
                  <hi>Here enſue certain holy Meditations of the <hi>7.</hi> Effuſions, diſtributed for the Canonical Houres.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="hour__matins">
                  <head>At Matins.</head>
                  <p>COnſider with devotion, and yield manifold thanks to our B. Saviour for the effuſion of his pretious blood, and ſuffererings in his Circumciſion, offering the dolours and pains of the ſaid effuſion to God the Father for all thoſe that are in ſtate of mortall ſin, that it would pleaſe his divine goodnes to give them a perfect knowledge of their offences with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, confeſſion, ſatisfaction and amendment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__laudes">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:150050:33"/>
                  <head>At Laudes.</head>
                  <p>POnder and give thanks for the dolorousneſſ, pain and effuſion of blood, which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour CHRIST JESUS endured in the garden a little before he was apprehended and taken, where with great pain and agony he ſweat blood and water: offering this ſpiritually unto God the Father for thoſe that are in the ſtate of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, favour and love of God, and his holy name, that it would pleaſe him to conſerve them in that ſtate and purity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__prime">
                  <head>At Prime.</head>
                  <p>YIeld many thanks for the pain and effuſion of blood, which our B. ſaviour CHRIST JESUS ſuffered in his flagellation, offering it up unto God the Father, for all thoſe that are in any affliction or tribulation, be it ſpirituall or corporall, beſeeching his divine Majeſty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve each one of them, as he knoweth to be moſt to his honour, and the health of their ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__terce">
                  <head>At Tierce.</head>
                  <p>IN devout contemplation give Many thanks unto God our ſweet Saviour CHRIST IESUS for the effuſion of his moſt precious blood which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150050:33"/> he endured in his crowning with thorns: offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it to God the Father for our parents, kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and benefactours, and all for whom wee are any wayes obliged to pray: beſeeching him to give them his holy grace to live in his true love and feare, and at their death to poſſeſs everlaſting life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__sext">
                  <head>At Sext.</head>
                  <p>YIeld manyfold thanks unto our B. Saviour IESUS for the paines and effuſion of his pretious blood, which iſſued forth of his hands and feet, being nailed on the Croſſ; offering it to God the Father for the ſtate of our holy Mother the church, that the Popes holines, and all Eccleſiaſticall Powers may be exalted, to the increaſe of his honour, and have grace ſtrength and ability, well to diſcharge what is committed to them therein.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__none">
                  <head>At None.</head>
                  <p>GIve manifold thanks unto our B. Saviour for the effuſion and shedding of his ſacred blood when nayled to the Croſs his moſt holy ſide was pierced with a lance; offering it to God the Father for the Converſion of all Hereticks: particularly for England, that it would pleaſe him to enlighten them with his holy grace to know and embrace the truth, that they with all
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150050:34"/> others may in union and perfect charity, love, praiſe and magnify him everlaſtingly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__vespers">
                  <head>At Evenſong.</head>
                  <p>CAll to mind the dolorous Myſtery of our B. Saviours taking from the Croſs and lying in the lapp of his Mother, offering it to God the Father for all religious perſons who are eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially dedicated unto his holy ſervice, beſeeching his divine goodnes to give each one of them grace perfectly to perforn his holy will even unto death, &amp; to live vertuouſly in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of their inſtitutes, and perſever therein untill the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="hour__compline">
                  <head>At Compline.</head>
                  <p>COnſider how our B. Saviour being dead and his holy body taken down from the Croſs, it was by our B. Lady, S. Mary Magdalen and other holy perſons laid in the ſepulcher whileſt his glorious ſoul deſcended into <hi>Limbo,</hi> where he delivered the juſt: all which with devotion wee may preſent unto God the Father for the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort and releaſement of the ſoules detained for the purging of their ſins in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> beſeeching him mercifully to receive them unto his happy reſt, that they may eternally praiſe him. AMEN.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:150050:34"/>
               <head>A Prayer after the Divine Office.</head>
               <p>O Good JESUS be propitious unto me a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner: unto thy goodnes do J com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this my office moſt coldly and diſtractedly accomplished, beſeeching that through your me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits it may be amended and perfected. Unto you good JESU do I offer it for the good of the whole church, and the ſalvation of my ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, in union of that moſt perfect attention, with which here on earth you did pray unto your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father; Anſwer I beſeech you, Satisfy, and pray for me. AMEN.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="devotion">
               <head>A Direction for Mentall Prayer.</head>
               <p>THoſe who deſire to increaſe and go forward in a ſpirituall life, let them go that certain way, which is the interiour and mutuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with Almighty God, performed in this holy Exerciſe. Becauſe in Prayer vertues are ceived, obtained, and augmented. <hi>Prayer</hi> as the holy Apoſtle S. James ſaith, <hi>availeth much,</hi> aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to heaven before the tribunall ſeat of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and bringeth unto men every good and perfect gift; cauſeth ſuch a league and union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and them, as it maketh their ſoules apt to receive infinite grace from his divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. Daniel by Prayer converted the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ of Lions into the meekneſſ of Lambs. Prayer
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150050:35"/> made the fire looſe its force, being not able to burn the three children in the midſt of the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming furnace. Prayer likewiſe ſtayed the courſe and altered the uniform motions of the heavens, giving power to the voyce of man to ſtop and detain the ſun for as many howers as was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the obtaining the victory againſt his enemies. Jacob through the vertue and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Prayer prevailed againſt the Angell. Yea Prayer tyed the hands and infinit power, (if we may ſo ſay) of the Lord of Angels: for by the Prayer of Moyſes Almighty God ſeemed to be as it were diſabled to chaſtize the people, when he ſaid unto this faithfull ſervant of his. <hi>Suffer me that my fury m y be angry againſt them:</hi> as if he should have ſaid: <hi>Detain me not with thy Prayers.</hi> Prayer finally obtaineth pardon for whatſoever offences: the Publican getteth remiſſion of his ſins, and the Prodigall child pardon, and returns again into favour by Prayer. Therfore it being ſo profitable and neceſſary for a ſpirituall life, obtaining by the vertue thereof whatſoever it will in heaven or Earrh; it is requiſit that all Religious perſons, ſpend as much time as their ſtate and leiſure will permit them in this kind of Prayer: which rather conſiſteth in the actions of the will then the long diſcourſe or ſpeculation of the underſtanding, ſenſible gifts, or conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: for that is not in our own hands. The fruit of Prayer is, that we raiſe from the ſame, <hi>humility, patience, obedience, Indifference &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:150050:35"/> This is alwaies in our power, (the grace of God preſuppoſed.) To the end that Prayer be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with Recollection and attention, it is neceſſary that we do not take it in hand as a thing of ſmall moment, not rashly, but adviſedly; not with a ſlow and dull heart, but with a lively attention, and undaunted courage: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we might incurr the curſe of the Prophet Jeremy, who ſaith, <hi>Curſed is he that doth the worke of the Lord negligently.</hi> Neither is ſo great atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and force to be uſed as therby to weary and break our heads, and hinder our health: for ſo, inſteed of pleaſant and ſweet milk we should <hi>wring forth blood,</hi> (as the wiſdom of God ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth in Proverbs) cauſe a feare and horrour to undertake this holy Exerciſe. Wherfore to avoid theſe extreams, Moderation is to be uſed in ſuch ſort, as by over much ſtriving therein we hurt not our ſelves, as was aforeſaid, nor through too much careleſneſſ let our mind be carried away with unprofitable matters Let not wandring thoughts trouble you, but put them away ſweetly: for you merit more by patient reſiſtance then in having great comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. Humble and accuſe your ſelf in the fight of Almighty God, that you cannot be ſo long in his preſence without ſo many earthly cogitations: beſeeching our B. Lady, your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angel, and all others with the Saints to pray for you and ſupply your wants in due praiſe and love of his divine Majeſty. For ſcruples and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150050:36"/> temptations, which happen in Prayer, the firſt remedy, is not to hearken, or give eare unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="instruction_for_prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>An Instruction for mentall Prayer to which are required <hi>5.</hi> Conditions. To wit.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="condition">
                  <head>1. <hi>Preparation.</hi> 2. <hi>Meditation.</hi> 3. <hi>Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</hi> 4. <hi>Colloquie.</hi> 5. <hi>Recollection.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. PReparation hath 4. conditions. The 1. which is univerſall to all piety, Purity of heart and calmneſſ of paſſions, and affections, and Recollection both of ſenſes and fancies: but above all things, that the intention be pure, and that you undertake this vertuous Exerciſe ſincerely for the love of God to pleaſe him, and reform your life and manners accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his moſt bleſſed will and not for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of conſolations or divine lights; which we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re an intention proper to hirelings, and not fit for his children, nor gratefull to our heavenly Father, who deſires above all things a pure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The 2. is Reading, which you may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome in this manner: read thoſe points you intend to make your Meditation on after even ſong, before or about dinner: and that which you purpoſe to meditate on after Mattins the night before. Ruminate the matter divers
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150050:36"/> times before you meditate, moving your ſelf to taſt and feel thoſe good motions and affections, which you think the matter will yield you to draw forth. For if in an affaire of importance which we handle with earthly creatures, we ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly think and conſider thereof before: how much more ought we to do it in this ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall an Exerciſe and the greateſt which can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be undertaken, being we are therein to treat with Almighty God about the good and ſalvation of our ſoule.</p>
                  <p>The 3. condition, is the Preſence of God. Coming to the place where you purpoſe to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate conſider the preſence of Almighty God comparing his greatneſſ and goodneſſ, with your own baſenes and vileneſſ and imagining our ſweet Saviour calleth you to shew you what he hath don, ſaid and ſuffered for you. Or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider your ſelf a beggar, ſick, and guilty, to crave of your benefactour an almes, of your Phyſitian health, and of your Judge pardon; beſeeching your good Angel, and ſome of your Patrons to accompany and aſſiſt you therein.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The 4. and laſt condition of preparation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is the Prayer preparatory, wherein you crave grace affectuouſly in generall to perform your Meditation to Gods honour and glory, and the good of your own ſoule, remembring that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. <hi>Omnis noſtra ſufficientia à Deo est.</hi> All our ſufficiency is from God: beſeeching your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father who is a ſea of mercies to rain down
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150050:37"/> by his power plenty of pious thoughts to poſſeſs your memory; God the ſon the true light and wiſdom to illuminate and inſtruct your Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with heavenly knowledge; God the Holy Ghoſt, who is an infinit burning fire of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to enflame your will with pious affections.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="condition">
                  <head>The <hi>2.</hi> Condition of Mentall Prayer is Preambles, which are for the moſt part three.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THe fitſt whereof is a tepetition to your ſelf as you would to another, of the matter, ſentence, or verſe, of which you are to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The 2. if the matter be Hiſtoricall, is to repreſent unto your ſelf the place and perſons preſent. As for example: Meditating ſome My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Chriſt, put before your eyes ſome moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, citty, or deſert, fitting the place to the Miſtery or ſentence, which you are to conſider. If what you purpoſe to meditate be ſpirituall matter, void of ſuch ſimilitude, abſtain from the 2. Preamble accordingly. If of Hell: think of the length, breadth, and depth of that horrid place, with all things that may give horrour unto If of Heaven: repreſent the ſpacious plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſſ of that Celeſtiall Country. If on death: your ſelf lying on your death bed, or laid in your grave. If on Judgement: our ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150050:37"/> ſitting on his Judgment ſeat. If on ſin: your ſoule to be held priſoner in your body, fettered with chaines of diſordered paſſions, and clogged with the burden of the flesh. But if the ſentence of your Meditation be ſuch, as cannot make theſe nor the former ſimilitudes: call to mind who ſpoke or did it, in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſort, or with what intention: reciting that ſentence two or three times unto your ſelf: which manner you muſt alſo accuſtome in all ſorts of Meditations, expecting what it shall pleaſe God to teach you: therfore ſaying: <hi>Speak Lord thy ſervant heareth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The 3. Preamble, or petition is briefly to crave light and knowledge of the Myſtery you meditate on, and grace to ſtirr up in your ſelf ſuch particular good affections of this or that vertue as you shall ſee the matter is moſt apt to miniſter occaſion, for your ſpirituall profit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="condition">
                  <head>The 3. Condition of mentall Prayer, is Meditation, which conſisteth in the three powers of the ſoule.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. FIrſt: let the memory remember to call to mind the preſence of Almighty God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom you are to chuſe the matter whereon you are to meditate, in what manner you are to do it, and the end wherfore.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly: the Underſtanding muſt diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150050:38"/> of the matter, whether it be of ſome perſon, as of our Saviour: ſome words of holy ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſome actions, as of the Paſſion of CHRIST JESUS, or the ſuffering of his Saints: the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, cauſe, properties, effects, conveniences, and circumſtances, as, WHO, WHAT, WHY, WHERE, WHEN, BY WHAT MEANS: And this is not to be don ſlightly, but very ſeriouſly, ſo as they may move the will, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and as it were shewing them again.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly: the will muſt ſtirr up in it ſelf theſe affections, and make ſuch good purpoſes as the ſubject doth require, and the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath before approved for good: ſeeking to perform towards God: 1. The affections of praiſe of his holy name. 2. Love of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſ. 3. Confidence in his mercy. 4. Faith in his verity. 5. Feare of his juſtice. 6. Gratitude for his benefits. Towards your ſelf, affections of love or hatred, deſire or disdain, joy or ſorrow, converſion, or averſion, feare or hope, diſlike or purſuit of the matter which you have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: and in theſe of the will you muſt incite and ſtay your ſelf in every point of your medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
                  <div type="advice">
                     <head>How to proceed with fruit in every point of your Meditation.</head>
                     <p>FIrſt the memory is to preſent the matter unto the underſtanding, as is above ſaid, and that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150050:38"/> is to conſider the perſons, actions, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances as is ſet down: and when by diſcourſe and particular view of the matter, you shal ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently underſtand any ſpeciall point to move affections: as to diſcover Gods goodneſs, love, or any benefit, don towards us by him, exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of vertue, or difformity of vice, then ſtay that diſcourſe, and ſeek to ſtirr up ſuch good affections, as the matter will moſt aptly afford. As for example; when by diſcourſe you have found the goodneſs of God, or ſome great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of him to us; then ſtay, love, view, and admire him for the greatnes thereof: inciting your ſelf to have a perpetuall memory and ack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowledgment of them, drawing ſomthing for your inſtruction and encouragement to his moſt perfect ſervice and your own progreſſ in vertue. This is a great part of the fruit, which you are to reap of Meditation, the which you muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by colloquy and Prayer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="advice">
                     <head>Helps, if the will do's not yield unto thoſe affections which you deſire.</head>
                     <p>REflect with your ſelf what affections ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations ought to move in you towards God, whoſe love, goodnes, and benefits you ſee to be ſo great, and you have deſerved ſo little: the which conſideration ought to produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in you exceeding great love, praiſe, gratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, obedience, confidence &amp;c. Then come to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150050:39"/> your will again, and ſee whether it will yield to thoſe affections. If it do not, then labour to move it either by ſuch perſuaſions as you would give to another, whom you deſire to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite to the ſame affections: Or elſe, reprove your dulneſſ; or ask your ſelf the queſtion <hi>why you should not yield thereunto:</hi> ſeeing that you can remember your ſelf and others to be exceedingly moved unto ſuch affections towards creatures for leſſ motives. And again ſay. <hi>Why should not I feel the like to my Creatour, or at leaſt yield with my will to deſire it, and purpoſe the ſame?</hi> Then have recourſe to Prayer and ſay. O my God, J will purpoſe &amp;c. J deſire you to aſſiſt me with your grace: confeſſing your miſery and unworthines, beſeeching him to be your help. And ſomtimes ſay theſe words of Jacob: <hi>I will not leave thee O Lord untill thou giveſtme thy bleſsing:</hi> or thoſe of the Cananean woman. <hi>Yes Lord I am a dog, yet doggs eate, the crums which fall from their Maiſters table:</hi> or other ſuch like. And thus, having at leaſt by ſome meanes or other ſtirred up the foreſaid affections, though not ſo fervently as we deſire, perſever in exerciſing the will, drawing forth ſomthing for your profit. This example, in due proportion may ſerve to teach you how to proceed upon any other matter: as when you have by diſcourſe diſcovered any vertue or vice in ſome <hi>word, deed</hi> or <hi>thought,</hi> of ſome perſon who is preſented in the Meditation: firſt by ſtaying or pondering, or ſometimes admiring
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150050:39"/> how worthy a thing that vertue is, in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and how foule the vice: the fruit and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit which ariſeth of the one, and the loſſ and shame of the other. Then proceed as you will to move and ſtirr up the affection you ſeek; never contenting your ſelf with generall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, be they never ſo fervent, nor ſpend to much time in them, but make ſome particular reſolutions, of which you ſtand in moſt need for the advancement and correction of your life, which having ſtirred up, confirmed, and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to practice, conclude alwaies the part, and much of the whole Meditation with devout col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquies or ſpeaches of heart unto Almighty God.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="condition">
                  <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Condition of Prayer, or Colloquy to be ſaid at the end of Meditation or part of them during the ſame.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THe firſt is to give God thanks for the holy affections, reſolutions, and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which he hath inſpired into you, as alſo for his goodnes and mercy which you have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in the diſcourſe of your Meditation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, by way of oblation, wherein you preſent unto God the ſelf ſame goodnes and mercy of his, which you have taſted in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation together with the death Paſſion, vertues and merits of his holy ſon our Redeemer, and conſequently with all the affections and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150050:40"/> which by his holy grace you made in your Meditation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly by Petition or Obſecration, which you demand of God, and earneſtly conjure him, as it were through the death and Paſſion of our fweet Saviour, the merits of the glorious Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary, the interceſſion of your good Angel, and all the holy Saints to bleſſ your affections and reſolutions, which to his honour and glory you have made, to the end you may faithfully put them in execution, and for making your ſelf more capable of his grace; crave pardon for your ſins and offences committed againſt his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, with remedy of ſome vice and augmentation of ſome vertue, offering your ſelf wholy unto his holy ſervice with a firm purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to avoid whatſoever may offend him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly; beſides theſe particular petitions which appertain unto your ſelf, it is very good to make a generall ſute for all both living and dead, but eſpecially for thoſe who have moſt need, and to whom you are moſt obliged, and particularly for the ſoules in Purgatory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="condition">
                  <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Condition of Mentall Prayer is Recollection.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, your Meditation being ended, it is very profitable to ponder well and conſider how it ſucceeded; whether you followed the method that was taught you, in the preparation, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150050:40"/> Meditation and all the reſt, and what point moved you moſt, and how you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed your ſelf therein, craving pardon for your defects, and giving Almighty God thanks for what was well, reſolving to follow what you ſee to be profitable unto you, and avoid the contrary.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You muſt have a particular care to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your felf unto thoſe good motions, which Almighty God shall give you in Prayer: for, ſo to do, is a moſt ſpeciall means to obtain the increaſe of grace: for the contrary would be an ingratitude and contempt of Gods graces, which deſerveth not to have the like hereafter: a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall help for the ſame is to have care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them: and for that end it is good at Maſſ, and the Divine Office to renew and offer them to Almighty God, and divers times in the day to do the like.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly, if at any time it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that through ill diſpoſition, want of due Preparation, or yielding to temptation, your Meditation doth not ſucced; be not diſmayed or diſcouraged, but humbling your ſelf in Gods ſight, acknowledge your imperfections and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligences; crave pardon of his divine Majeſty, purpoſing by his holy grace to be more carefull and diligent the next time: for the obtaining of which, have confidence in his divine goodnes, and thank him that he hath vouchſafed to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt you the favour to be ſo long in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150050:41"/> And if it were to have the leaſt good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in all the time of your meditation, or but a remembrance of Almighty God, think not the time loſt, and labour fruitleſſ, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if you wil make uſe of that little you have by often remembring it, doubt not but that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpark by laying wood to it, and often blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the coales will turn to a great fire of the love of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advice">
               <head>An advice how to overcome ſome diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that fall out in Meditation.</head>
               <p>THe firſt is when you find your ſelf without guſt of devotion, and ſo dry that Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will not only ſeem to be cumberſom unto you, but alſo time loſt. To overcome this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty: you muſt underſtand, that aridity and drineſſ may come ſomtimes out of your own fault; as when you uſed not that diligence you ought either in meditation, or in preparing your ſelf, by foreſeeing what you are to meditate on, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as hath been ſaid, whereof it cometh, that you do it with negligence, &amp; dryly: and Almy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty God in punishment thereof doth worthily deprive you of the conſolation and taſt of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. The remedy to rid your ſelf of this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment, is to take away the cauſe. At other times this aridity cometh without fault; and we muſt not therfore leave Meditation: for as a time of conſolation doth pleaſe you, when our
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150050:41"/> Lord like the ſun in the ſpring cometh neare to you, and mak's you have guſt in meditation: ſo you muſt not be diſpleaſed or leave your Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, when the ſelf ſame ſaviour as the ſun in winter doth go from you, which he alſo doth for your good, that you may plant roots of humility, exerciſe patience and reſignation, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing that when he goeth from you, you remain dry without devotion, having confidence that God will accept of your Meditation and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, and ſend you conſolation when he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth moſt fitting; and perſevering with courage and hope, remember the words of Tobias. <hi>Qui poſt tempeſtatem, tranquillum facit. Who after a ſtorme mak's a calme.</hi> As alſo that of Job. If <hi>we have received good things, why should not we beare with the basd.</hi> It may be alſo that Almighty God ſuffereth you to be dry in Prayer, to try with what intention you come to ſo holy an Exerciſe: proving whether you be his ſouldier for payment, expecting he should reward you with guſt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion: or elſe to make you know that your taſt and comfort in meditation is his gift, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d when he will, that by this means you diſpoſe your ſelf to ask humbly of him, and with confidence expect what you aske<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoever you prav to pleaſe God therby as you ought to do; you may ſay: I did not begin my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to feel guſt or devotion, but for the love of God, my ſweet ſaviour JESUS, &amp; for his love I will continue it.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:150050:42"/>
               <p>Another difficulty is, that the divell will repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Meditation unto you, as very hard and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, ſo to make you differr it, and afterwards wholy forſake it. But if you have a true deſire to do a thing acceptable to your Creatour, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Meditation will not ſeem ſo tedious or you will hold all well employed for his love. How many courtiers do you ſee going a hundred times a yeare unto the Princes chamber without hopes of once ſpeaking unto him, onely to be ſeen-by him, that he may take notice how they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to shew their duty unto him: ſo muſt you come to the Exerciſes of Prayer, which is as it were Gods Chamber of Preſence purely and meerly to do your duty and teſtify your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity. And if it pleaſe him not to ſpeak to you, no otherwiſe then if he ſaw you not, or if you were not in his preſence, you muſt not for all that go away diſcontented, or diſcomforted, but continue ſtill with patience and a devout beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in the preſence of his ſoverain goodnes: and without doubt your ſervice will be acceptable to him, and at laſt he will take notice of your conſtancy and diligence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditations">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:150050:42"/>
               <head>Colloquies or ſpeeches, part in Meditation and part in Prayer; Praiſing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Gods Excellency, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, holineſs, worthineſs &amp;c.</head>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>TO THE SOULE.</head>
                  <p>EXhorting it to ſome vertuous action: ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reprehending her vices and faults, little zeal, imperfections &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>PURPOSES.</head>
                  <p>Purpoſing to Gods honour, Obedience, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Reſignation, Mortification &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>AFFECTIONS.</head>
                  <p>More affections towards God, increaſe of his honour, augmentation of the Church, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>SUPPLICATION.</head>
                  <p>Make ſupplication unto God, as a ſon does to his father, a beggar to his benefactour, a ſick man to his Phyſitian, a ſchollar to his Maſter, and a ſpouſe to her bridegroome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>TO OUR B. LADY.</head>
                  <p>Alleadging that shee is our mother, Miſtris, Queen and Advocate, and therfore ought and doth love us, defend, protect, and pray for us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:150050:43"/>
                  <head>TO OUR GOOD ANGEL.</head>
                  <p>Alleadging his office, charge, and power to help us: his honour to defend us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>TO THE SAINTS.</head>
                  <p>Eſpecially thoſe to whom you are moſt devoted, alleadging their affinity to our nature, their tryalls of our neceſſities, their ſecurity in glory, and their ability and willingnes to help us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>CAUSES OF DISTRACTIONS.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt from the Divell who doth ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to hinder from the fruit of Prayer.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It proceedeth from our own imagination which is free, untamed, and ill governed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From ſome affections unmortified, which draw our thoughts after them, for <hi>where the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, there is the heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. From cares which ſting, and divide the heart into a thouſand parts.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. From coldnes in enforcing our ſelves to this ſo noble an Exerciſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. From ignorance, not knowing how to diſcourſe or meditate, or ſearche into hidden ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and ponder them in ſuch ſort as may move the will and ſtirr up affections of devotion. This ignorance by the grace of God will be remedied by this form, and method following.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="advice">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150050:43"/>
               <head>The meanes to reſist diſtractions of heart and tediouſnes of spirit, are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally foure.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt, profound humility, acknowledging our weakneſs and miſery; being ashamed to ſtand before God with ſuch diſtractions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing our ſelves of our offences both paſt and preſent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond, fortitude of mind, reſolving not to admit any diſtraction, although it admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter matter of content, of ſeem of much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance; for nothing behoveth us ſo much as to tend to Prayer and to God, before whom we are. Wherfore if a thouſand times we should be diverted, we muſt turn again as many times more, without looſing courage.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The thrid remedy, Prayer it ſelf: beſeeching our ſaviour to recollect our thoughts and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring affections, that wee may uſe attention and devotion: craving the help and interceſſion of his glorious Mother with the holy Angels and Saints, who are willing to aſſiſt all thoſe that pray: ſaying ſomtimes with David. <hi>My heart hath forſaken me, may it pleaſe you Lord to deliver me from the violence which I ſuffer, and have reſpect to help.</hi> Other times with the Prophet: <hi>My ſoule is as earth without water.</hi> Again: with the blind
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150050:44"/> man in the Ghoſpell. <hi>O ſon of David have mercy on me.</hi> Or with the Pſalmiſt. <hi>Depart from me o yee malignants, and I will ſearch the Commandements of my God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth is Confidence in Almighty God: perſuading our ſelves, that being he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us to pray, he will give us grace wherby we may reſiſt the divell, bridle our imaginations, reſtrain our paſſions, moderate our cares, caſt from us our coldneſs: But with this confidence wee muſt adjoyn diligence, as Caſſian ſaith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving before Prayer whatſoever you think may diſtract you therein: imitating in this the ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our adverſary; who as S. Nilus Abbot ſaith, <hi>ordaineth all his temptations, wherwith he tempteth ſp rituall perſons, to hinder them from Prayer &amp; the fruit thereof: tempting them with impatience to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet them, curioſity to diſtract them, multitude of buſines to disturb them, pride and ingratitude to make them barren and dry &amp;c.</hi> By this we may learn to be no leſs provident and carefull of our good then the divell is of our harm, ever governing our ſelves in ſuch ſort as may moſt forward our Prayer, remembring the words of our ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in S. Luke. <hi>It behoveth us alwaies to pray, and never to be weary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The chiefeſt effects of prayer.</head>
               <p>ARe particular lights, affections, and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions. And whatſoever elſe is needfull for
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150050:44"/> a large Examin after Meditation, is ſet down in the end of the book of the practice of Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſolation is an inward motion unto the more perfect love of God, and withdraweth our affections from all earthly creatures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Teares, ſpringing of love or ſorrow, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtly ordained to the honour of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Increaſe of hope and Charity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Joy and devotion, which incites the ſoul unto greater perfection.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Illuminations of the underſtanding, wherby it underſtandeth ſome things anew or better, and more perfectly then before.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Deſolation is that which vaileth the eyes of the ſoul, that it may not behold that which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the glory of God, and the perfection of the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which troubleth, and moveth us to earthly and outward things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That which draweth us to the diſtruſt of obtaining perfection, or what may help us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That which driveth away Hope and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That which bringeth the ſoule to a certain tepidity, heavines, and tediouſnes of mind. S. Bernard ſpeaking of the devout Meditation upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Paſſion of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, ſaith thus. <hi>If thou deſireſt perfectly to be purified from all thy ſins and vices, if thou wouldſt be nobly enriched with vertues, illuminated in holy Scripture: if thou would'ſt gloriouſly
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150050:45"/> triumph over thy enemies: if abundantly be conforted in adverſities; if often, to have compunction and shed teares of devotion: if to obtain the burning fervour oſ ſpirit in Meditation: if to be replenished with ſpirituall joy, if to perſever in well doing, if in the end well and bleſsed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to dy, and to reign in heaven eternally: and finally to be beloved and crowned by our Saviour Ieſus, ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly, exerciſe thy ſelf in the holy Meditation of the bleſſed life and Paſsion of Ieſus, and often reduce the ſame unto thy heart and memory.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Things to be conſidered in Meditating the Paſſion of our Saviour.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Who it is that ſuffereth. 2, What it is he ſuffereth. 3. How he ſuffereth. 4. For whom 5. To what end he ſuffered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Severall Affections to be draw'n from the conſideration of the ſame Paſſion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. To have compaſſion on the greatnes of his pains.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Contrition for the ſins, which were the cauſe of his ſufferance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Imitation in folowing his examples.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Gratitude for the largeneſſ of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hope he dyed to ſave us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Love in ſeeing the greatneſſ of his love.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Admiration in beholding his unſpeakable
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150050:45"/> bounty and goodnes. It is written of him, <hi>dixit multa, fecit mira, pertulit dura.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Conſiderations of the knowledge of ones ſelf.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider what you have been, what you are, and what you shall be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ponder what you are by nature: by fault, what you have deſerved; and what you may do by grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The effectuall cauſe of your Being, is God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The matter of which you are made is Earth, agreeing with the nature of beaſts.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Our ſoules to the image of God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Our end to ſerve him, and live eternally with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Conſiderations of ſin.</head>
               <p n="1">1. How much it diſpleaſeth Almighty God, and hurteth man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How contrary to his juſtice, diſpleaſing, and diſedifying to our neighbour.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God's ſevere punishment of it, and what we looſe therby.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The diſguſt that followeth ſin, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour that accompanieth it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The grief of God, his Angels, and Saints, with the joy of the Divell.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The difformity of ſin, and the disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between men and it, according to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſ of the ſoul.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150050:46"/>
               <head>How to conſider Death.</head>
               <p n="1">1. That all muſt neceſſarily dy, and then be deprived of all things.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Onely accompanied with grief and ſicknes of the body, with temptations and feares of the ſoule.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And nothing will confort you at that hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re but only good works.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Death ought not to be feared, contemned, or deſired.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Of the Pains of the damned.</head>
               <p>There are many waies to meditate of this, as in that which followeth of glory, only chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the good for the evill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>To contemplate Heaven.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider the dowries of the ſoule, which are the viſion, poſſeſſion and enjoying of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The dowries and perfections of the body: Impaſſibility, Brightnes, Agility, Subtility.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The place: moſt excellent, moſt large, moſt beautifull and moſt rich.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The company of the Angels and Saints with the Bleſſed Mother of God, which shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for all Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:150050:46"/>
               <head>How to conſider vertue.</head>
               <p n="1">1. In what vertue conſiſteth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What examples and doctrine my ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour hath given you thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How beautifull, excellent, neceſſary, and profitable it is: how pleaſing unto God, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth man agreable to him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How much it edifieth and profiteth your neighbour.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The ſpirituall joy it bringeth with many benefits.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The victory we gain therby over our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="7">7. How farr we are from the perfection the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof and what you ought to do hereafter.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The power we gain therby, in preſenting our Prayers to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>How to conſider the Feaſts of Saints.</head>
               <p n="1">1. In what place they are now and with what glory they are crowned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How much they may help us by their Prayers and merits.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By what works, Prayers, and vertues they have attained ſuch glory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If you will come where they are, do as they have don.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:150050:47"/>
               <head>To meditate on the Perfections of Almighty God.</head>
               <p n="1">1. His infinit Eſſence. 2. His Power. 3. His Wiſdome. 4. His Bounty. 5. His Goodnes 6. His Love. 7. His Mercy. 8. His Juſtice. 9. His Providence. 10. His Omnipotency: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which weigh this ſentence of holy ſcripture, or what himſelf hath don in teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony thereof. <hi>Caelum &amp; terram ego impleo. In ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vivimus, movemur &amp; ſumus. I fill heaven and Earth. In him we live, move, and are.</hi> For his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. <hi>Dixit, &amp; facta ſunt. He ſaid, and they we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re made.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Conſiderations of the creatures of Almi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty God, &amp; firſt in generall.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BY the largeneſs of the world, conſider the greatnes of Almighty God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The multitude and variety of things with the infinit perfections of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His bounty in the profit they bring unto us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. His beauty by the beauty of the creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</p>
               <p n="5">5. His wiſdom in the well ordering of all things.</p>
               <p n="6">6. His Eternity, in the roundneſs, which hath neither beginning nor end.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:150050:47"/>7. The unity of the world, shewing that God is only one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The creatures in particular, their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and continuance which is of God.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The end thereof, to wit his honour, and the ſervice of creatures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of what and how they were made by his only word and power.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The qualities and effects of theſe creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, the reverence they uſe unto God and his perfections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The benefits in brief of Almighty God.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Who hath don you the benefit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Who hath moved him to do it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Wherfore he hath don it unto you.</p>
               <p n="4">4. How great the benefit is.</p>
               <p n="5">5. How much you are obliged therby,</p>
               <p n="6">6. How ungratefull you have been.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>What you ought to do in the time to come with the benefits of Almighty God in particular.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt how God hath predeſtinated us in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall love before the world was.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How he hath made man like to himſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:150050:48"/>3. Given you a body of moſt ſeemly features void of all defformity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Made your ſoul immortall, and adorned it with three powers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Appointed an Angell to keep and defend you.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Made you to be born of Chriſtian parents, and members of the Church,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The benefit of our Redemption.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt ſent us his well beloved ſon to be our Redeemer and example.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By Baptiſme purged you from orignal ſin and reſtored you the veſture of originall juſtice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Fortified you with the Sacrament of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, wherby he hath armed you againſt your enemies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Made you a Chriſtian, and therby the child of God and coheire of his Kingdome.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hath given the holy Ghoſt in token of adoption of love, communicating unto you his benefits inſpirations and fruits.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Laſtly the Sacraments of Confeſſion and Communion, as a refuge in all Spirituall relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and neceſſities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The benefit of vocation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt the patience of Almighty God with you: you falling ſo often after ſo many great
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150050:48"/> benefits received, long expecting your return, and not letting you dy in an evill ſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sought to recall you by inward inſpirations admonitions, and exhortations.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Mollified your heart, giving you a good will to vertue, and removed ſuch impediments as might withdraw you from him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Lovingly received you at your return, as the Father did his prodigall child, putting on you the ſtole of innocency, which you had loſt by ſin.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Hath called you from the vanities and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of the world, as he did Lot from Sodom.</p>
               <p n="6">6. What great plenty of means he hath given you in Religion, wherby you may ſatisfy for your ſins, increaſe your crown and merit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The benefit of juſtification.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt how God hath changed your will, and moved you to do pennance, made bitter things ſweet, and that which was unſupportable to be eaſy unto you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, he hath given unto you perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance in his feare and love: many begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning well have failed in the end to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly he hath given to you the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall vertues of hope and grace, to perſever in your good purpoſes to avoid vice and labour for vertue.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:150050:49"/>4. Fourthly hath left the holy ſcriptures and devout books, wherein as in a glaſs you may behold your defects and imperfections.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly, the examples of Martyrs, Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, Virgins, and the daily edification of thoſe with whom you live.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The benefit of donation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt the gift of nature, fortune, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: as the five ſences with the three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour powers of your ſoul, health, ſtrength, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God brought you back when you were aſtray, inſtructed you when you were ignorant, and lifted you up when you were fallen.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly enlightned your underſtanding when it was in darkneſs of ſin, and ſtirred up in you many good motions and deſires.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Moved your will and affections to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall works and exerciſes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Preſerved you from many enormous ſins, taking from you the occaſions, and giving you grace to perſever and reſiſt them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Delivered you from divers ſorts of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, drawing you forth when you were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm'd in them, and given you greater force to reſiſt them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:150050:49"/>
               <head>The benefit of Preſervation,</head>
               <p n="1">1. PReſerved you both ſpiritually and corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in a good ſtate, with increaſe of good deſires, to execute good purpoſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the cradle to this moment preſerved you from many enemies, diſeaſes, dangers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hath hitherto furnished you with all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries both ſpiritual and corporall.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Ordained for you ſucceſſion of times, as day and night, winter and ſummer &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Directed you in proſperity and adverſity, in ſicknes and healthe, and in the whole courſe of your life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The benefit of Glorification.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe fruition of the divinity with the viſion of God, and his B. Mother.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The company of your good Angel with the Martyrs, Confeſſors Virgins, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The dowry of the ſoule: the glorification of the body more bright and cleare then the ſun it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="4">4. the place of the bleſſed, the delights of the ſenſes, the riches and abounding pleaſures of the inhabitants, which are innumerable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable, and immeaſurable.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By the grace of God you shall ſcape the torments of Hell: the miſeries of this life: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150050:50"/> hurts and cruelties of your mortall enemies.</p>
               <p>Theſe Meditations are as it were a cord to draw you unto Almighty God. Gratitude is a great part of juſtice, and amongſt all Chriſtian exerciſes none is more eaſy, if you be willing: none more needfull, if you regard your duty: none more profitable, if you deſire reward, then often to look over the great and manifold bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, which we have received of Almighty God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>The eight Beatitudes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>BEati pauperes ſpiritu, quoniam ipſorum eſt re|'gnum coelorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit, for theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Poverty of ſpirit
<list>
                     <item>Acknowledgeth her ſins. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneth her ſelf. Deſpiſeth none. Honoureth all.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Beati mites quoniam ipſi poſsidebunt terram. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the meek, for they shall poſſeſs the land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meekneſſe
<list>
                     <item>Anſwereth ſweetly. Admonisheth benignly. Is mild being reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Behaveth her ſelf piouſly.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Beati qui lugent quoniam ipſi conſolabuntur. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thoſe that mourn for they shall be comforted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sorrow
<list>
                     <item>Excludeth all glory. Abideth in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, For the love of her neighour. For her own ſins.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Beati qui eſuriunt &amp; ſitiunt juſtitiam quoniam ipſi ſaturabuntur. Bleſsed are they that humger and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150050:50"/> thirst juſtice for they shall be ſatiated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hunger and thirſt
<list>
                     <item>Hath horrour of vice: A fervour of ſpirit: Tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of temporall things: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Eternall.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Beati mundo corde, quoniam ipſi Deum videbunt. Bleſsed are the Cleane of heart, for they shall ſee God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Purity of heart
<list>
                     <item>Is ſincere in intention: Right in works: Excludeth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe cogitations: Aſſiduous in contemplation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Beati miſericordes, quoniam ipſi miſericodiam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentur. Bleſſed are the mercifull, becaus they shall find mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mercy
<list>
                     <item>Hath compaſſion in tribulation.</item>
                     <item>Succoureth in neceſſities.</item>
                     <item>Delighteth in liberality.</item>
                     <item>Is benigne with affability.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Beati Pacifici, quoniam filii Dei vocabuntur. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are the Peace makers for they shall he cal'd the children of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Things which work Peace
<list>
                     <item>Silence and ſolitarineſs.</item>
                     <item>Frequent and devout Prayer.</item>
                     <item>Fervent contemplation.</item>
                     <item>To admit no interiour trouble.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Beati qui perſecutionem patiuntur prvpter juſtitiam, quoniam ipſorum eſt regnum coelorum. Bleſſed are they that ſuffer perſecution, for theyr's is the kingdome of Heau'n.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:150050:51"/>
               <p>Things which produce Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.
<list>
                     <item>Feare of eternall ſufferance.</item>
                     <item>Fervent love of God.</item>
                     <item>Memory of the Paſſion of our Saviour.</item>
                     <item>Hope of Eternall joy.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>A Religious perſon ought often to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the benefit of his vocation by theſe circumſtances following.</head>
               <p>VNDE ES? Quo? Quomodo? Quando? Quo fine vocatus?</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> FROM WHENCE, God, to wit, hath called you? From the world, the gulfe of ſin and evils.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2. WHITHER? TO</hi> holy Religion, the houſe of God, the ſchool of vertue, the gate of conſolation, and the pourtrait of the celeſtiall Ieruſalem.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> HOW? With what love, wiſdom, and power he called? without your own merit.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> WHEN? In your youthfull, or old age, when you leaſt deſired or ſought after ſuch a courſe.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Laſtly for what END? <hi>1.</hi> To ſerve God perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, and forſake all things to accomplish it. <hi>2.</hi> To do pennance, beare your Croſs, and follow the ſteps of Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>3.</hi> To work your ſalvation and to gain perfection. <hi>4.</hi> To help your neighbour as much as is poſsible according to your vocation and inſtitution by good example and prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Bernard had this ſentence alwaies in his heart.</hi> Bernarde ad quid veniſti? Bernard, to what end didſt thou come hither?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150050:51"/>
               <head>The Priviledges and benefits of a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſon.</head>
               <p>Homo vivit puriùs, cadit rariùs, ſurgit velociùs, incedit cautiùs, quieſcit ſecuriùs, irroratur frequentiùs, mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur confidentiùs, purgatur citiùs, remuneratur copioſiùs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>A Religious perſon.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>LIveth more purely:</hi> by the obſervance of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, Chaſtity and Obedience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Falleth more rarely:</hi> by flying the occaſions of ſin and perverſe converſation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Riſeth more quickly:</hi> by conſideration of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures; the lives of Saints, and example of thoſe with whom we live.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Walketh more warily:</hi> by meditating their ſins paſt, imperfections preſent, and the joy which cometh of vertue.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Resteth more ſecurely:</hi> by attaining the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, and interiour conſolation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Receiveth more grace:</hi> by bettering their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and becoming more familiar with God.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Dyes more confidently:</hi> by the the efficacy of Priviledges in Religion, meritorious works and help of Communaulty, with the imitation of their ſpouſe CHRIST JESUS.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Is ſooner purged:</hi> by the many remedies to make ſatisfaction, by the multitude of holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations, and frequent exhortations.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:150050:52"/>
               <p n="9">9. Is <hi>rewarded more abundantly:</hi> becauſe a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious life is victorious over her enemies the <hi>FLESH,</hi> the <hi>WORLD,</hi> and the <hi>DIVELL.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="daily_aspirations">
               <head>JESUS MARIA. Certain Aſpirations for every day in the weeke.</head>
               <div n="Monday" type="day">
                  <head>Munday, Humility.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. WHen shall it be my God, that J shall be ſo odious, execrable, and inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to my ſelf, as J deſire to be afflicted and punished of all creatures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O ſweet Saviour, when shall it be, that J shall have ſuch a true contempt of my ſelf, as with all my heart J wish to be contemned and reputed of every one, moſt vile.</p>
                  <p n="3">3, When shall J, deare JESUS, for the love of, you deſire in ſuch ſort to be humbled, as J be ever reduced to nothing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O moſt meek Lord, J confeſſ before thee, and will acknowledge to all the world, that J am the moſt vile and unprofitable of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O my God there is not on earth to be found a creature ſo diſloyall and ungratefull as J am unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. J am not worthy to look up to heaven, and much leſſ to poſſeſſe the ſame.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:150050:52"/>
                  <p n="7">7. If the greateſt ſinner in the world had tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe inſpirations, and daily means of vertue, which J, o Lord, confeſſ to have: J verily think he would not be ſo wretched as J am.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Tuesday" type="day">
                  <head>Tueſday, Confidence.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. ALthough every moment, deare JESUS, J commit many imperfections, yet J ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe by thy help to attain to Chriſtian perfection.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. My ſweet Saviour, if J committed all the ſins and crimes, which have been from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, yet would J be confident of pardon.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. J hope moſt firmely, O ſon of God, my Redeemer, by thy holy merits and Sacraments to enjoy eternall life.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O infinit clemency! was there ever any ſinner that truly asked pardon, to whom you denied it?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. My ſweet Saviour: if all creatures both in heaven and earth should tell me that thou hadſt forſaken me, and didſt refuſe to help me, yet J would not beleeve them.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O ſweet JESU; albeit the furies in Hell, together with all the afflictions of this life should torment me, yet would J truſt in thee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O good JESUS: thou that ſaid'ſt. <hi>Aske and it shall be given: beleeve, and you shall receive:</hi> J humbly beg, and unfainedly confide in thy goodnes, whatſoever is neceſſary for me, either ſpirituall or corporall thou wilt give me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Wednesday" type="day">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:150050:53"/>
                  <head>Wednſday, Poverty.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. O My Lord, J deſire no riches, eaſe, or ſenſuall delights, but only the love of thee.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O that J had a thouſand worlds, with all the fained pleaſures thereof, not to poſſeſſe, but willingly to leave for the love of thee.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Moſt deare Lord, J will poſſeſs nothing but thee, and what J have, only for thy ſake.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O deareſt ſpouſe all riches without thee are unto me unſupportable poverty: joy, ſorrow, eaſe, paine, conſolation, a conſuming grief.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O my ſweet Saviour that was't both in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe and death ſo poor and naked of all things: for thee I moſt willingly embrace the want of what is neceſſary for corporall life and health.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. My ſweeteſt Jeſu, which was't ſo poor and free from the poſeſſion of your will even in the repugnance of death: for thee, I entirely forſake my own will and ſence to the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of my life.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O my deareſt Saviour that Wouldſt not admit in all thy torments the leaſt comfort, I beſeech thee make me ſo perfectly poore as for thy love I entertain no unneceſſary conſolation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Thursday" type="day">
                  <head>Thurſday, Gratitude.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. O my good God I render thee eternall thanks for all thy gifts both of grace
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150050:53"/> and nature beſtowed on me and on all creatures.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O moſt liberall God thou haſt don to me above all I can ask or deſire.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. O my Saviour what shall J render for all thoſe numberleſſe benefits, which I have and continually do receive from thee?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O deare Saviour in gratitude for all thy mercies towards me, I offer and beſeech thee to accept of my heart and ſoule, with what elſe thou haſt beſtowed on me.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O my Creatour and deare Redeemer, that I could be gratfull unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Teach me, my God, to render thee ſuch thanks as may be moſt acceptable unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O would to God I had the gratitude of creatures both in heaven and earth to offer up unto thee my onely good: but all being too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, I beg thou wilt thy ſelf ſupply theſe wants.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Friday" type="day">
                  <head>Friday, Obedience and Reſignation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. O Moſt benigne Lord, let me but know what you would have me to do.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sweete Jeſus I offer my ſelf both in time and Eternity, moſt entirely to accomplish thy will.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Although J should be loſt, yet if it be thy will: for love of thee I moſt willingly yield to live in continuall affliction and torment.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I offer my ſelf with all my heart, my ſweete Saviour, in what I may poſſibly,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150050:54"/> in body, life and ſoule to be diſpoſed of, by thy bleſſed will and pleaſure.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Behold, ſweet Lord for love of thee, I abandon and deny my ſenſes, renounce my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and wholy forſake my ſelf to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve, and accomplish thy holy will.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Moſt deare God, for thy ſake I firmly purpoſe, rather to dy a thouſand deaths then once to be diſobedient to thee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O good Jeſus, when shall I ſee that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py houre, wherein by perfect obedience and entire Reſignation I shall wholy live in thee, and thou in me.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Saturday" type="day">
                  <head>Saturday, Love of neighbour.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. MOſt mercifull Lord, I beſeech thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit goodnes, ſo to illuminate the hearts of all ſinners, that they may be truly penitent for their ſins, to ſeek thee with all care who art the onely God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I beſeech thee my ſweet Lord by the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of thy infinit mercies, that all ſuch as ſeek after ambition and earthly delights, may turn all their affections to love thee.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Grant ſweet Jeſus through the merits of thy bitter Paſſion, that all thoſe for whom thou haſt ſuffered, may reape the benefit thereof.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Moſt mercifull Lord, I humbly beſeech thee to comfort all afflicted ſoules.</p>
                  <p n="5">5, Moſt ſweet Saviour; give ſuch grace and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150050:54"/> vertue unto all creatures, as they may be truly conformable unto thy holy will.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Moſt mercifull God, releaſe for thy own ſake, and thy B. Mother's, all thoſe who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Earth or Purgatory, thou doſt by ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice punish.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Sunday" type="day">
                  <head>Sunday, Love of Almighty God.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. TAke form me. O ſweet Saviour, that which ſeparateth me ſo farr from thee.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Purge my ſoule, O Lord, from all ſin, and imperfection, by which it is defiled, and made unworthy of thy Image.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Behold, O my God, I hate and deteſt with all my heart, even the leaſt offence that ever I have committed againſt thy divine Majeſty.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Forgive, ſweet Saviour, all that which juſtly thou mighteſt lay to my charge: for that now I deſire to be perfectly united unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. My ſweeteſt Lord, as a channell of all uncleanneſſe deſirous to be purified, I preſent my ſelf unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O Eternall God, I beſeech thee, that I who am the leaſt of all creatures, may by perfect love of thee, be elevated above all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted things, and my ſpirit only ſatisfied in thee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What shall I render thee my beloved Lord for all thou haſt beſtowed on me, that am but duſt and ashes and yet thou haſt made all things for me.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="daily_aspirations">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:150050:55"/>
               <head>Aſpirations for every day in the Weeke upon the Paſſion of our bleſſed Saviour.</head>
               <div n="Monday" type="day">
                  <head>Munday, Contrition.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. O Vile and moſt deteſtable ſin, by which I have ſo oft betrayed and ſold thee my Eternall Father: yea even for a momentary pleaſure.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O that I had never by ingratitude bound thy liberall hands, and therby deprived my ſelf of thee, and of thy will, and mercifull plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in me.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. O my ſoule unto what ſtreights have thy ſins and offences brought thy Saviour: would to God I had ſome ſeas of teares to shed for having thus often cruelly tormented thee.</p>
                  <p n="4">4, O, if it had been thy will, my ſweeteſt Jeſu, I wish I might have endured, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly temporall but endleſs pains, rather then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve cauſed the leaſt part of thy affliction.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O Sacred wounds of my deareſt Saviour in revenge of my cruelty, wound my heart with ten thouſand darts of true remorſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O ſin how deformed and unjuſt art thou, that thus has't defiled the beauty of heaven and crucifyed my Immaculate Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O that I might with a thouſand millions of lives, and infinit ſeas of blood, blot out
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150050:55"/> of my ſoule the guilt of thy death and Paſſion.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Sweet Jeſus ingulfe and drown me in thy ſacred wounds, that there I may learn to love.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Tuesday" type="day">
                  <head>Tueſday, Compaſſion.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. O That I could shed for thee my Lord ſo many teares as the ſea contains drops of water, in true compaſſion of thy torments.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O who will give water to my head, and a fountain of teares to my eyes, to weep upon thee, the love of my ſoule.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. O love, and only comfort of my heart, what conſolation hadſt thou in all thy torments?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Alas, my well beloved; why am not J alwaies preſent to ſuffer with thee, at leaſt by compaſſion on thy pains.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. My ſweet JESUS, O that I might be crucified with thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O love of my ſoule, that I might have had the priviledge of the launce to have reſted in thy heart.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. My deareſt Saviour permit me the favour to remain at the foot of thy Croſs, to the end that I may weep continually, ſigh, bleed, cry, and conſume in compaſſion of thee.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Give me an endleſs ſpring of teares, to wash away the ſacred blood of my ſweeteſt love, which ſtill iſſueth as flowing rivers from thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Wednesday" type="day">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:150050:56"/>
                  <head>Wenſday, Imitation.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. O Moſt ſweet JESUS: give me grace in imitation of thy ſacred Paſſion, moſt willingly to undergoe the burthen of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory life.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For that thou haſt ſuffered ſo many and cruell torments for my ſake; let me never, O mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, fly any tribulation, which thou shalt vouchſafe to ſend me by thy ſelf or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. My Jeſus, to accompany thee in thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold afflictions, I would be glad, not onely to endure the wants which thou ſendeſt me, but ſeek others, and never be ſatisfied in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering with thee.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In imitation of thy nakedneſs, reproaches and whippings at the pillar; I will endeavour to ſtrip my ſelf of all inordinate deſires and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. I will continually follow thee my dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Saviour with the Croſſe of perfect obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and never for any difficulty leave the ſame till I come to dy with thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O my Eternall God, that wouldſt for my ſake be nailed to the Croſs: let me by true mortification be alwaies crucified with thee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. My loving ſpouſe, I beſeech thee, that with a full renunciation of my ſelf, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall death of all earthly things I may irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocably dy with thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Thursday" type="day">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:150050:56"/>
                  <head>Thurſday, Thankſgiving.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. WHat thanks shall I yield unto thee my Eternall life, who wouldſt endure unſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peakeable torments to free me from the ſnare and fetters of death.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. All you ſeraphins, and celeſtiall Spirits, with whatſoever hath been created praiſe my Redeemer for the unſpeakeable price of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. O my ſoule: how can'ſt thou deviſe to render the leaſt part of due gratitude unto thy Jeſus, who hath by his own humility ſo much exalted thee.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O let me ever acknowledge, my deare Saviour, that endleſs bond of gratitude, which thy Paſſion alone exacteth of me.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Sweet JESUS, that I could inceſſantly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve thee, for theſe ineſtimable treaſures, which thou by thy torments haſt purchaſed unto me.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Good IESUS; ſince I have nothing but my ſelf to offer in requitall of thy infinit love: I beſeech thee to accept in love and gratitude what by-right is thy own.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O eternall God, that I had a thouſand hearts and lives to offer unto thee, who by thy death haſt given and bequeathed thy ſelf to me.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Grant, ſweet IESUS, that thy dolorous death and Paſſion be ever imprinted in my heart my true thankfulneſs and imitation thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Friday" type="day">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:150050:57"/>
                  <head>Friday, Admiration.</head>
                  <p>O My God, who art thou, who haſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured ſo many and cruell torments? ſweet and deareſt love haſt thou forgotten thy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and glory?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O light of heaven, and ſplendour of thy Fathers glory, unto what art thou now redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Alas, my Saviour, what art thou who art ſo deſpightfully treated?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O love of loves, that through the exceſs of thy love, thou wouldſt for me endure ſo bitter a death.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O love how ſtrong art thou, which with thy force ſurmounted'ſt him, that by no other means may be overcome.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O incomprehenſible God, for whom doſt thou ſuffer, but for miſerable ſinners, ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull creatures, thy enemies, children of the divell, and thoſe who contemn thee.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. O deareſt love; that my heart is not pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with thy dolours.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. What were it o Lord, if I had all the loves of the world to unite and offer unto thee?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. My ſweet IESUS, if I could reduce all thy drops of blood into teares of love, what were it compared unto thy love?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Saturday" type="day">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:150050:57"/>
                  <head>Saturday, Ioy.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. My heart and ſoule rejoyce and praiſe the mercies of my God who out of his infinit love hath died to give thee life.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O my delight, what joy will it give to my heart to receave that life, that infinit good, through the merits of thy moſt bitter and dolorous paſſion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Sweet JESUS, I praiſe thee with eternall joy for having in thy moſt cruell death ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly accomplished the work of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It was by thee, O beloved Croſs, that peace hath been eſtablished between God and man.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O triumphant glory, and moſt puiſſant King who by thy moſt ſacred death, haſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Prince of Hell, and delivered our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les out of his bondage.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. O Heaven, Earth, ſea, and all things therein; yield praiſes in our behalf unto the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of our ſoules; and let us rejoyce in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of his ſacred paſſion.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. If all my members were tongues, O how willingly would I employ them in the praiſe of thee my ſweet ſaviour, and thy health-brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging wounds.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. O all yee celeſtiall ſpirits aſſiſt me to love and praiſe my God, by the vertue of whoſe Paſſion your ruins are repaired.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:150050:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p n="9">9. Sweet JESUS, what glory and comfort is it unto human nature to be exalted in thee, unto the right hand of thy Eternall father.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Sunday" type="day">
                  <head>Sunday, Love.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. When shall it be, my crucified JESUS, that both the ſenſes of my body, and powers of my ſoule shall be wholy employed in thy praiſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. O my JESUS, when by perfect love and imitation shall I be daily crucified, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually dy with thee.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. O my beloved JESUS, when shall I love thee in ſuch ſort, as that thy ſacred wounds be by burning love imprinted in my heart.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. O my beloved JESUS, when wilt thou bring me into the wine cellar of thy bleſſed ſide and make me wholy drunke with the moſt ſacred wine, which floweth from thy loving heart.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. O when shall it be, my deareſt JESU, that the flame of thy love shall pierce and wound my heart, that I may be wholy conformable unto thee.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sweet JESUS let me love thee ſo unfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly as that by force of thy love, I neither feel, ſee, nor take comfort in any thing, but accompanyng thee my afflicted Lord.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. My ſweeteſt Saviour, when shall I have my full and wisht repoſe within thy crucified armes.</p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:150050:58"/>
                  <p n="8">8. O ſacred wounds of my JESUS, eſpecially of his tender ſide, and moſt amou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous heart, why do you not burn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume my ſoule in the delightfull flames of his love.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="oblation">
               <head>An Oblation unto our B. Lady to ſay on any one of her Feaſts <hi>70.</hi> Ave Maries, and then during every day <hi>5.</hi> Ave's and theſe Prayers following.</head>
               <p n="1">1. O B. Virgin Mary, and Eternall Queen of Angels, I offer my ſelf unto you in all that I am, or ever shall be, beſeeching you to receive me as your own.</p>
               <p n="2">2. O B. Virgin Mary, preſerve me living and dyng from all evill, for I am your own.</p>
               <p n="3">3. O B. Virgin Mary, receive me for your own, ever govern, and protect me as your own and have mercy on my ſoule, when it shall part out of my body.</p>
               <p n="4">4. O mercifull Mother, through your holy departure, make joyfull my departure, and in the houre of my death, receive my ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version__prayer">
               <head>A Prayer to Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <l>ANima Chriſti ſanctifica me,</l>
               <l>Corpus Chriſti ſalva me,</l>
               <l>Sanguis Chriſti inebria me,</l>
               <l>Aqua lateris Chriſti lava me.</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:150050:59"/>
               <l>Paſsio Chriſti conforta me,</l>
               <l>O bone IESV exaudi me,</l>
               <l>Intrà tua vulnera abſconde me,</l>
               <l>Ne permittas me ſeparari à te,</l>
               <l>Ab hoſte maligno defende me,</l>
               <l>In hora mortis meae voca me,</l>
               <l>Et jube me venire ad te,</l>
               <l>Vt cum Sanctis tuis laudem Te</l>
               <l>In ſaecula ſaeculorum Amen.</l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version__prayer">
               <head>In English thus.</head>
               <l>SOule of Chriſt ſanctify me,</l>
               <l>Body of Chriſt ſave me,</l>
               <l>Blood of Chriſt inebriate me,</l>
               <l>Water of Chriſt's ſide wash me,</l>
               <l>Paſſion of Chriſt comfort me,</l>
               <l>O good JESU heare me,</l>
               <l>Within thy wounds hide me,</l>
               <l>Suffer me not to be ſeparated from thee,</l>
               <l>From the malignant enemy defend me,</l>
               <l>In the houre of my death call me,</l>
               <l>And bid me come to thee,</l>
               <l>That with thy Saints I may praiſe thee</l>
               <l>For ever and ever, Amen.</l>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version__devotion">
               <head>When you paſse by the B. Sacrament.</head>
               <p>DVlciſsimum nomen Domini nostri Ieſu Chriſti, &amp; glorioſae Virginis Mariae Matris ejus ſit in ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternum benedictum.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version__devotion">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:150050:59"/>
               <head>In English.</head>
               <p>Let the B. Name of our Lord JESUS CHRIST and the glorious VIRGIN MARY, his MOTHER be bleſſed for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>And then offer your intention herein to get the pardon which is gained.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version__devotion">
               <head>When you take Holy water.</head>
               <p>Aqua benedicta, ſit nobis ſalus, protectio &amp; vita. Aſperges me Domine hiſſopo, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version__devotion">
               <head>In English.</head>
               <p>May this holy water be to us health, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and life. Thou shalt ſprinkle me o Lord with hiſſope, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="version__verses">
               <head>How we may honour the moſt holy and B. Name of the most glorious Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by ſayng theſe <hi>5.</hi> Verſes with <hi>5.</hi> Pſalmes.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>MAter amabilis Maria nomine,</l>
                  <l>Multò nobilior quocunque lumine.</l>
                  <l>Muni me miſerum in tuo nomine,</l>
                  <l>Malignis obvians tuo juvamine.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Magnificat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:150050:60"/>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>Aurora rutilans lunâque pulchrior,</l>
                  <l>Astris fulgentior, &amp; luce clarior,</l>
                  <l>Afflictum reſpice qui nimis crucior,</l>
                  <l>Averte jaculum hoſtis quo ferior.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad Dominum cum tribularer.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Regina nobilis, filia filii,</l>
                  <l>Roſae conſimilis &amp; flori lilii,</l>
                  <l>Refove flebiles lacte conſilii,</l>
                  <l>Ruentes per dies huius exilii.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Retribue ſervo tuo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>Ieſſe tu congruè vocata virgula</l>
                  <l>Immarceſsibilis &amp; ſine macula,</l>
                  <l>IESV jam florid o qui regit ſaecula,</l>
                  <l>Ipſa tu ſuggere ut ſolvat vincula.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In Convertendo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>Ancilla Domini ſumens tam nobilis</l>
                  <l>Ave, quod Gabriel dedit mirabilis,</l>
                  <l>Accipe canticum ſervi inutilis,</l>
                  <l>Adſis in omnibus mihi placabilis.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad te levavi.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>℣. Dignare me laudare te Virgo ſacrata.</l>
                  <l>℟. Da mihi virtutem contra hoſtes tuos.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
               <head>OREMUS.</head>
               <p>COncede nos famulos tuos, quaeſumus Domine Deus, perpetuá mentis &amp; corporis ſanitate gaudere, &amp; glorio â B. Mariae Virginis interceſsione, à praeſenti libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari triſtitia, &amp; aeternâ perfrui laetitiâ. Per Chriſtum Domenum nostrum. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version__verses">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:150050:60"/>
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Verſes Englished.</head>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>O Amiable Mother ô Mary hail by name,</l>
                  <l>More noble then the light of natur's frame,</l>
                  <l>Defend me, by your meanes, which way ſo'ere J goe,</l>
                  <l>And by your shelt'ring help, preſerve me from my foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>Bright shining dawn, fairer then the moon,</l>
                  <l>More ſparkling then the ſtarres, and brighter then the ſun,</l>
                  <l>Look on me, wretch afflicted, and tormented, ſo,</l>
                  <l>As to put by thoſe darts, my foes do at me thr'o.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>O noble queen, and daughter to thy ſon,</l>
                  <l>Like to the Roſe and Flower-de-Luce at noone,</l>
                  <l>'Tis milk of your good counſel, muſt cherish us that weep,</l>
                  <l>'Tis you that from all banish't ruin's, muſt us keep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="4">
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>You are the rod of Jeſſe fittly nam'd,</l>
                  <l>You neyther wither, nor with spot are sham'd,</l>
                  <l>Pray to our Jeſus, who the world doe's rule</l>
                  <l>That J from bonds of ſin, may ſave my ſoule.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="5">
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>O handmaid of our Lord, who took the noble haile</l>
                  <l>From wond'rous Gabriel's mouth, the world's great baile,</l>
                  <l>Receive the ſacred Cantick, your worthleſs ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant ſing's,</l>
                  <l>And gratious be to me, ſweet Mary in all things.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="litany">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:150050:61"/>
               <head>LITANIAE B. P. N. FRANCISCI.</head>
               <list type="litany">
                  <item>KYRIE eleïſon. Chriſte eleïſon.</item>
                  <item>Kyrie eleïſon. Chriſte audi nos.</item>
                  <item>Chriſte exaudi nos.</item>
                  <item>Pater de caelis Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Fili Redemptor mundi Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Spiritus ſancte Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Trinitas unus Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Franciſce, Pater amabilis, ora pro nobis.</item>
                  <item>Pater admirabilis,</item>
                  <item>Pater benigne,</item>
                  <item>Pater venerabilis,</item>
                  <item>Vexillifer Jeſu Chriſti, ORA PRO NOBIS.</item>
                  <item>Eques Crucifixi,</item>
                  <item>Imitator filii Dei,</item>
                  <item>Seraphim ardens,</item>
                  <item>Fornax Charitatis,</item>
                  <item>Arca Sanctitatis,</item>
                  <item>Cultor pacis,</item>
                  <item>Vas Puritatis,</item>
                  <item>Norma Juſtitiae,</item>
                  <item>Speculum Pudicitiae,</item>
                  <item>Regula Poenitentiae,</item>
                  <item>Magiſter Obedientiae,</item>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:150050:61"/>
                  <item>Exemplar Virtutum,</item>
                  <item>Patriarcha Pauperum,</item>
                  <item>Profligator Criminum,</item>
                  <item>Lumen tuae Patriae,</item>
                  <item>Decus Morum,</item>
                  <item>Vivificator Mortuorum,</item>
                  <item>Saturator Famelicorum,</item>
                  <item>Obſequium Leproſorum, ORA PRO NOBIS.</item>
                  <item>Praeco magni Regis,</item>
                  <item>Forma Humilitatis,</item>
                  <item>Conſors Sublimitatis,</item>
                  <item>Victor Vitiorum,</item>
                  <item>Dux Minorum,</item>
                  <item>Praedicator Silveſtrium,</item>
                  <item>Portans dona Gloriae,</item>
                  <item>Auriga militiae noſtrae,</item>
                  <item>Novis utens Prodigiis,</item>
                  <item>Caelum caecis aperiens,</item>
                  <item>Gratum gerens obſequium,</item>
                  <item>Templum Chriſto conſecrans,</item>
                  <item>Hoſtes malignos proterens,</item>
                  <item>Tenens vitae bravium,</item>
                  <item>Spargens virtutum munera,</item>
                  <item>Amplians iter ad Gloriam,</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Parce nobis Domine.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Exaudi nos Domine.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>℣. Ora pro nobis beate Pater Franciſce.</item>
                  <item>℟. Ut digni efficiamur promiſſionibus Chriſti.</item>
               </list>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:150050:62"/>
                  <head>OREMUS.</head>
                  <p>DEus qui Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> B. Frauciſci meritis foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu novae prolis amplificas: tribue nobis ex ejus imitatione terrena deſpicere, &amp; caeleſtium dono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſemper participatione gaudere. Per Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num noſtrum, &amp;c. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="litany">
               <head>LITANIAE B. M. N. CLARAE, VIRGINIS.</head>
               <list type="litany">
                  <item>KYrie eleïſon, Chriſte eleïſon. Kyrie eleïſon.</item>
                  <item>Chriſte audi nos. Chriſte exaudi nos.</item>
                  <item>Pater de caelis Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Fili Redemptor mundi Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Spiritus Sancte Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Trinitas unus Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Maria, Ora pro nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Dei Genitrix,</item>
                  <item>Sancta Virgo Virginum,</item>
                  <item>Sancta Clara Virgo Mater noſtra.</item>
                  <item>Virgo Chriſti Sponſa, ORA PRO NOBIS.</item>
                  <item>Virgo Franciſci plantula,</item>
                  <item>Virgo electa prae millibus,</item>
                  <item>Virgo Seraphica,</item>
                  <item>Virgo Matris Jeſu diſcipula,</item>
                  <item>Virgo primogenita pauperum,</item>
                  <item>Virgo gemma Virginum,</item>
                  <item>Virgo norma Perfectionis,</item>
                  <item>Virgo humillima,</item>
                  <item>Virgo mundo abſcondita,</item>
                  <item>Virgo ſpeculum Paupertatis,</item>
                  <item>Virgo Lilium caſtitatis,</item>
                  <item>Virgo roſa paenitentiae,</item>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:150050:62"/>
                  <item>Virgo Crucifixi amore ſaucia,</item>
                  <item>Virgo crucis ardentiſſima amati</item>
                  <item>Virgo ſtella clariſſima,</item>
                  <item>Virgo ſequens Agnum quocunque</item>
                  <item>Mater noſtra honorificata,</item>
                  <item>Mater admirabilis,</item>
                  <item>Mater amabilis,</item>
                  <item>Mater ſicut balſamum aromatizans, ORA PRO NOBIS.</item>
                  <item>Mater paranympha Chriſti,</item>
                  <item>Mater pulchrae dilectionis,</item>
                  <item>Mater puritatis nutrix,</item>
                  <item>Mater Obedientiae magiſtra,</item>
                  <item>Mater ſcala Paradiſi,</item>
                  <item>Mater gloria Filiarum,</item>
                  <item>Mater ſocia Angelorum,</item>
                  <item>Mater clipeus in te ſperantium,</item>
                  <item>Mater protectrix Pauperum,</item>
                  <item>Mater conſolatrix flentium,</item>
                  <item>Mater terror Infidelium,</item>
                  <item>Mater triumphatrix daemonum,</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis &amp;c. Parce &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis &amp;c. Exaudi nos &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis &amp;c. Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>℣. Ora pro nobis Beata mater Clara.</item>
                  <item>℟. Ut digni efficiamur promiſſionibus Chriſti.</item>
               </list>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
                  <head>OREMUS.</head>
                  <p>FAmulos tuos quaeſumus Domine, beatae Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis tuae Clarae votivam commemorationem recenſentes, caeleſtium gaudiorum ſuâ facias in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terventione participes, &amp; tui Unigeniti cohaere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Per eundem Dominum noſtrum &amp;c. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="litany">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:150050:63"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IESVS MARIA.</hi> Litaniae dicendae pro converſione Anglia ad Religionem Catholicam.</head>
               <list type="litany">
                  <item>KYRIE eleïſon. Chriſte eleïſon.</item>
                  <item>Kyrie eleïſon. Chriſte audi nos.</item>
                  <item>Chriſte exaudi nos.</item>
                  <item>Pater de coelis Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Fili Redemptor mundi Deus, miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Spiritus ſancte Deus, miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Trinitas unus Deus, Miſerere nobis.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Maria, Ora pro nobis</item>
                  <item>Sancta Dei genitrix, ora &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Virgo Virginum, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Michaël, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Gabriël, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Raphaël, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſancti Angeli &amp; Archangeli, orate.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſacti beatorum ſpirituum ordines, orate &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Joannes Baptiſta, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Joſeph, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſancti Patriarchae &amp; Prophetae, orate.</item>
                  <item>S. Petre. ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Paule, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Andrea, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Jacobe, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Joannes, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Thoma, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Jacobe, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Philippe, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Bartholomaee, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Mathaee, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Simon, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Thadaee, ora.</item>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:150050:63"/>
                  <item>S. Mathia, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Barnaba, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Luca, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Marce, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſancti Apoſtoli &amp; Evangeliſtae. orate.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Joſeph ab Aremathia, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſancti Diſcipuli Domini, orate.</item>
                  <item>S. Eleutheri, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Victor, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Albane, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Georgi, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Thoma, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Juli &amp; Aron, orate.</item>
                  <item>S. Socrates &amp; Stephane, orate pro nobis.</item>
                  <item>S. Euvalde, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Kiliane, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Oſualde, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Rumolde, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Bonifaci, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Colmanne, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Augule, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Alphege, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Livine, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Edmunde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Eduarde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Kenelme, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Arnulphe, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Clare, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes Sancti Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, orate.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Gregori, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Auguſtine, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Celeſtine, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Palladi, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Patrici, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Carole, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte David, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Melite, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Julte, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Germane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Lupe, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Quintigerne, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Niniane, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Erconvalde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Felix, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Corentine, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Cedda, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Aidane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Eadberte, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Willibrorde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Aſaphe, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Beane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Mackure, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Ethelnolde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Donſtane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Honori, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Cuthberre, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Sampſon, ora.</item>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:150050:64"/>
                  <item>Sancte Maglori, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Manſuete, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Mallone, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Laurenti, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Suiberte, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Pauline, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Suithune, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Wolſtane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Oſualde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Vito, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Walfride, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Richarde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Theodore, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Joannes, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Hedde, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Wolfranne, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Gilberte, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Malachia, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Thoma, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Berine, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Aldelme, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Oſmunde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Laurenti, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Edmunde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Anſelme, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Hugo, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſancti Pontifices &amp; Confeſſores, orate.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Eduarde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Edilberte, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Sebbe, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Richarde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Brandane, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Columbane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Galle, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Dei-Cola, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Columba, ora</item>
                  <item>Sancte Querare, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Joannes, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Winoce, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Caniſe, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Egberte, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Willebalde, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Fintane, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Benedicte, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Beda, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Fiacri, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Furſee, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Guthlaci, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancte Roberte, ora.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſancti Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Monachi &amp; Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitae, orate.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Maria Mag. ora</item>
                  <item>Sancta Vrſula &amp; So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciae, orate.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Wenefrida, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Dympna, ora</item>
                  <item>Sancta Brigida, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Thereſia, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Editha, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Ediltrudes, ora</item>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:150050:64"/>
                  <item>Sancta Hilda, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Edilburga, ora</item>
                  <item>Sancta Ebba, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sacta Oſita, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Milburges, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Vereburga, ora</item>
                  <item>Sancta Fredeſuida, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Thecla, ora,</item>
                  <item>Sancta Batildes, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Lioba, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Cuthburga, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Syra, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Walburga, ora.</item>
                  <item>Sancta Margarita, ora.</item>
                  <item>S. Helena, ora pro nobis.</item>
                  <item>Omnes ſanctae Virgines &amp; Viduae, orate pro nobis.</item>
                  <item>Propitius eſto, parce nobis Domine.</item>
                  <item>Propitius eſto, Exaudi nos Domine.</item>
                  <item>Ab inſidiis diaboli, Libera nos Domine.</item>
                  <item>A neglectu inſpirationum tuarum, Libera nos Domine.</item>
                  <item>A mala &amp; pertinaci voluntate, Libera.</item>
                  <item>A caecitate cordis, libera.</item>
                  <item>A morte perpetua, libera.</item>
                  <item>Per myſterium ſanctae Incarnationis tuae, libe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ra nos Domine.</item>
                  <item>Per Nativitatem tuam, libera.</item>
                  <item>Per infantiam tuam, libera.</item>
                  <item>Per diviniſſimam vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuam, libera,</item>
                  <item>Per Paſſionem &amp; mortem tuam. libera.</item>
                  <item>In die judicii, libera.</item>
                  <item>Peccatores, Te rogamns audi nos.</item>
                  <item>Vt nobis parcas, Te rogamus.</item>
                  <item>Vt Eccleſiam tuam ſanctam regere, &amp; tueri dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris, Te rogamus.</item>
                  <item>Vt Sacerdotes in Britannia, pro Religione Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica laborantes, cuſtodire &amp; adjuvare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneris, Te rogamus audi nos.</item>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:150050:65"/>
                  <item>Vt Britanniam ad Catholicam Fidem &amp; unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Eccleſiae revocare digneris, Te rogamus &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>Vt nos exaudire digneris, Te rogamus audi nos.</item>
                  <item>Fili Dei, Te rogamus audi nos.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Parce nobis Domine.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Exandi nos Domine.</item>
                  <item>Agnus Dei qui tollis peccata mundi, Miſerere nobis.</item>
               </list>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
                  <head>Oremus.</head>
                  <p>MEntes noſtras, quaeſumus Domine, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racletus, qui à te procedit, illuminet &amp; inducat in omnem, ſicut tuus promiſit Filius, veritatem.</p>
                  <p>COncede, miſericors Deus, fragilitati noſtrae praeſidium, ut qui ſanctae Dei genitricis memoriam agimus, interceſſionis ejus auxilio à noſtris iniquitatibus reſurgamus.</p>
                  <p>OMnipotens ſempiterne Deus, qui ſaluas omnes, &amp; neminem vis perire; reſpice ad animas Britannorum diabolicâ fraude deceptas, ut omni haereticâ pravitate depoſitâ, errantium corda reſipiſcant, &amp; ad veritatis tue redeant unitatem. Per Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>DEO GRATIAS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="daily_prayers">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:150050:65"/>
               <head>A DAYLY EXERCISE OF PRAYERS With weekly Meditations upon the Paſſion.</head>
               <div type="prayer__morning">
                  <head>IN THE MORNING.</head>
                  <p>IN nomine Patris † &amp;c. Pater: Ave: Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do: Confiteor: &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>I adore thee moſt Bleſſed Trinity, &amp; give thee thankes for all benefits beſtowed upon me, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, for my Vocation to this State, the uſe of Sacraments, &amp; other Divine helpes; &amp; particularly, that thou haſt preſerved me this night, wherein perhaps many have been ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned before thee, to give an account of their lives; The living O God shall bleſs &amp; glorify thee, as I will this day.</p>
                  <p>O Eternall Father, to thee I offer up my ſelf, with whatſoever I am able to doe; admit O Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Father, theſe firſt fruites of my love, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the merits of thy beloved Son.</p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:150050:66"/>
                  <p>O B. JESUS, I purpoſe through thy Grace, to walk the paths of thy H. Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, performing the duty of a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian by the practiſe of all Vertues, eſpecially of N. Grant O Lord, that I may doe &amp; ſuffer all things, according to thy Holy will.</p>
                  <p>Come O Holy Ghoſt, direct, aſſiſt &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my diſtreſſed Soul, with thy Grace, that I may shun all Sin, eſpecially N. I have hitherto greivouſly offended thee, but I will be more watchfull over my wayes; Help me I beſeech thee in this my ſpirituall warfar, for thou haſt promiſed, that I shall walk amongſt Serpents &amp; Baſilisks, &amp; trample over Lyons &amp; Dragons.</p>
                  <p>Help me alſo O Holy Angels &amp; glorious Saints, thou eſpecially O Sacred Virgin Mother, with thy chaſt Eſpous S. JOSEPH. Protect me O Angell Guardian, &amp; Yee O Holy NN. my Patrons for this day; that I fall not into the ſnares of Satan. But thou O my God &amp; my All, art my cheife hope; let the flames of thy Divine Love conſume all evill affections in me, that I may for ever love &amp; obey thee.</p>
                  <div type="oblation">
                     <head>AN OBLATION.</head>
                     <p>O B. JESUS, in union of thy N. I offerr up all my thoughts, words &amp; deeds, purpoſing to practiſe the Vertue of N. &amp; shun the Vice
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150050:66"/> of N. beſeeching thee, that all I doe or ſuffer, may be acceptable to thee, for NN. through the Mediation of my glorious Patrons NN. Amen.</p>
                     <p>BLeſs me O JESU, with thy Sacred Virgin Mother † Bleſs me all yee Holy Saints &amp; Angels, ſpecially my Angell Guardian, &amp; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Patrons NN. †. O Eternall God, Father, Son, &amp; H. Ghoſt, bleſs † &amp; keep me, now &amp; for ever. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer__evening">
                  <head>IN THE EVENING.</head>
                  <p>IN nomine Patris &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>O Moſt Bleſſed Trinity, I glorify thee with all the Saints &amp; Angels, for all favours, at all times beſtowed upon me, eſpecially this day. <hi>(make a ſurvey of Gods favours to thee.)</hi> Alas what thankes can I return to thee, for theſe, &amp; all thy gracious benefits?</p>
                  <p>O God who haſt obſerved all the motions of my heart, &amp; all my words &amp; actions, Enlighten me, that I may know wherein I have offended thee, &amp; what is wanting to me, that I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayl my ſins, &amp; through thy Grace amend my life. <hi>(Examine thy conſcience through all houres &amp; duties of that day, towards God, thy Neighbour, &amp; thy ſelfe; conſidering wherein thou haſt offended by thought, word or deed.)</hi> Lord be mercifull to me
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150050:67"/> a ſinner! Behold here my God, what ſins I have rendred thee for thy gracious gifts; It greives me, that, I have offended thee; Pardon me O my God, through the Croſs &amp; Paſſion of thy deareſt Son, the merits of the Sacred Virgin, &amp; all Angels &amp; Saints, eſpecially N N. I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe hereafter never more to offend thee, &amp; to undergoe all Croſſes for the ſatisfying my tranſgreſſions againſt thee, &amp; purchaſing Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, for the amendement of my life.</p>
                  <div type="oblation">
                     <head>AN OBLATION.</head>
                     <p>O B. JESUS, I offer up to thee, thy N. as a propitiation for all my ſins, eſpecially of this day; Uniting therewith the merits of thy Sacred Mother, &amp; all Angels &amp; Saints, eſpecially my Patrons NN. to whoſe protection I now &amp; for ever commend my ſelf.</p>
                     <p>Bleſs me O JESUS &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="daily_meditations">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:150050:67"/>
               <head>MEDITATIONS VPON THE PASSION. For every day of the week.</head>
               <div n="Sunday" type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SUNDAY.</hi> Washing of the Feet.</head>
                  <p>CONS. 1. Who washeth? God, thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, Redeemer &amp; giver of all good things.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whoſe feet he washeth? of ignoble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, great ſinners, &amp; his own betrayer.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Why he washeth? to give example of meekneſs, &amp; teach us to cleanſe our Soules, ere we approach his Altar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect:</hi> Oh my JESU, that I could love thee &amp; all creatures, as I ought, &amp; thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolve,</hi> To practiſe the Vertue of <hi>Charitie,</hi> &amp; shun the vice of <hi>Envie,</hi> in occaſions beſt known to thy ſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Monday" type="day">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:150050:68"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>MUNDAY.</hi> Prayer in the garden.</head>
                  <p>CONS: 1. How CHRIST prayeth, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, proſtrate, &amp; with inſtancy: &amp; thou how tepid.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What's his prayer? That his Chalice may paſſe, yet with reſignation to obey his Fathers will: doe thou pray thus.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How he ſweats, bloud, in great drops, in great ſorrows; wilt thou rely on thy own ſtrength?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect:</hi> Oh my JESU, that I could humble my ſelf to Thee, &amp; all creatures for thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Roſolve,</hi> To practiſe <hi>Humilitie</hi> &amp; shun <hi>Pride,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Tuesday" type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>TUESDAY.</hi> Mocking before Herod.</head>
                  <p>CONS: 1. How JESUS betrayed, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, &amp; manicled, is led to Annas, Caiphas, Pilate &amp; Herod: Follow him in this ſorrowfull Pilgrimage.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:150050:68"/>2. How He is every where falſly accuſed, &amp; yet is ſilent; be ſilent too, when injur'd.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How before Herod, he is cloathed &amp; mocked as a Foole; if thou beeſt a Chriſtian, imitate CHRIST'S ſelf-denyall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect:</hi> Oh my JESU, that I could contemn my own will for thy ſake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolve,</hi> To practiſe <hi>Self-denyall,</hi> &amp; shun <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Wednesday" type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>WEDNESDAY.</hi> Whipping at the Pillar.</head>
                  <p>CONS: How JESUS led back to Pilate, is there accuſed as a Blaſphemer, Seducer &amp; Traitor; Barabbas though a Murderer, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd before him; can'ſt thou repine, when vilified?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How that Innocent Body uncloathed, &amp; bound to the Pilar, is whipt for thy ſins: thou ſin'ſt, &amp; he ſuffers.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How barbarouſly thoſe Soldiers treat thy JESUS; Oh cruelty! this he ſuffers for thee: Bath thy heart in his ſaving bloud.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect.</hi> Oh my JESU, that I could bear all
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150050:69"/> Croſſes, from all perſons, for the love of Thee</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolve,</hi> To practiſe <hi>Patience,</hi> &amp; shun <hi>Anger,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Thursday" type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THURSDAY.</hi> Crowning with Thorns.</head>
                  <p>CONS: 1. How JESUS thus bleeding, is crownd with sharp Thorns; this Crown is inſtead of a Crown of Glory.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How they cloath him in ſcarlet, put a reed in his hand for a Scepter, &amp; then kneeling deride Him. O my JESU thou art a King indeed; reign for ever in my heart.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How JESUS, thus adorned is led forth by Pilate, &amp; shown to the Jewes, with, <hi>Behold à Man:</hi> O ſad Spectacle! Yet ſtill, they cry, <hi>Crucify Him:</hi> Oh! the heavy weight of my ſins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect:</hi> Oh my JESU, that I could obey Thee, even to loſs of life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolve,</hi> To practiſe <hi>Obedience</hi> &amp; shun <hi>Sloath,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Friday" type="day">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:150050:69"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>FRYDAY.</hi> Carrying the Croſs.</head>
                  <p>CONS: 1. How JESUS thus derided, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped &amp; crowned, goes forth carrying the Croſs, whereon he is to be ſacrifized for thy Sins.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What shouts of joy the Jewes make after Him, through the ſtreets of Jeruſalem: thus is Innocency deſpiſed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How the devout woemen meet &amp; bewaile Him: thy hard heart sheds not one Teare amidſt theſe his ſorows, or for thy own ſins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect.</hi> Oh my JESU, that I could abandon all ſenſuall ſatisfactions for the Love of Thee!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolve,</hi> To practiſe <hi>Temperance,</hi> &amp; shun <hi>Gluttony,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Saturday" type="day">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SATURDAY.</hi> Crucifying of Ieſus.</head>
                  <p>CONS: 1. How JESUS with much pain &amp; shame, arrived to Mount Calvary, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain uncloath'd, &amp; thus all his ſoares are rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed: My Sins not blotted out by Repentance, shall one day be diſcloſed to the whole World.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:150050:70"/>2. How they ſtreatch thy JESUS upon the Croſs, faſtning him with nayles therunto, &amp; then raiſe him up, where he hangs between two theeves: Oh what ignominy!</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How He there hangs for the ſpace of three houres, reviled by Jews &amp; Gentiles, forſaken by his Diſciples, drenched with gall &amp; vineger, peirced to the heart with a ſpeare, yet He prays for his Enemies: Enter, &amp; make thy aboade in that love-wounded-Heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Affect:</hi> Oh my JESU that I could imitate Thee in the purity of thy Life &amp; Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſolve,</hi> To practiſe <hi>Modeſty</hi> &amp; shun <hi>All con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Therunto,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Woodcut illustration of the crrucified Christ, with two male figures standing to either side.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="method">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:150050:70"/>
               <head>A Method for Meditation.</head>
               <p n="1">1. PReparation hath 3. parts. Preſence of God, Choyce of matter, and Invocation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Meditation it ſelf hath 3. parts. Conſideration, Affection, and reſolution.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Concluſion hath 3. parts. Thanks-Giving, Oblation and Prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:150050:71"/>
               <head>A Prayer before Meditation.</head>
               <p>O my God, my Sovereign, my Creatour and my All; I here moſt humbly proſtrate my ſelf with the profoundeſt adoration J am poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly capable of, before your devine Majeſty, ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly imploring à continuance of your bleſſings vpon me, your poor needy Creature, and that you would be pleaſed out of your infinite boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by meanes of your holy ſpirite ſo to illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate my vnderſtanding, inflame my will, recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect from diſtractions and ſtrengthen in good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions all the powers of my ſoule, as that J may worthily, attentively and devoutly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this ſublime exerciſe of mentall prayer J am now vndertaking, to your honour and glory, the comfort of my own diſtreſſed ſoule, the joy of the Saints in heaven, and the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of men on earth, thro' your mercyes the meritts of my Bleſſed Saviour and the inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your Coeleſtiall Paraclet Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:150050:71"/>
               <head>A Prayer after Meditation.</head>
               <p>BEhold O my God, Behold, o my moſt patient and merciful Lord, how J have paſſed over this time of Meditation, and treating with thee; with how much negligence, sloth, coldnes, and diſtraction, and with how litle feeling of thy good motions within me: but thou O Lord knoweſt all my infirmities and Miſeries and therfore J crave of thee pardon for them. J thank thee alſo moſt heartily and humbly, for all the good thoughts and ſuggeſtions, which have preſented themſelves to my mind, in time of this my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, as moſt holy Embaſſadours ſent from thy heavenly Throne, to deale with me for the gaining of thy kingdome; whos bleſſed voices and moſt profitable ſpeeches, J beſeech thy divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne goodnes, to give me grace to imprint in my heart, and ſeeke to put in execution, in the cours of my life to come: to the end that my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Damnation, be not the more grievous in reſpect of thes thy Benefits, but rather that my life being mended therby, and my ſoul ſtirr'd up to more zeale of thy ſervice, J may be finally made partaker with thy true Children, of that eternall blïſs which thou haſt prepared, for ſuch os love, feare and ſerve thee and yeeld obedience to thoſe holy inſpirations which thou ſendeſt them for their eternal happines, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="table_of_meditations">
               <pb n="126-127" facs="tcp:150050:72"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A Table of dayly Patrons, Meditations Vertues, vices, and Intentions.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">Day.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Patron.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Meditation.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Vertue.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Vice.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Intentions.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sund.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>H. Angels.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>washing feet</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Charity.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Envie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For the H. church.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Mund.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Prayer in the Garden.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Humility.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pride.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For Vnion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Tueſd.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Mocking.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Self denyall</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Self love.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For benefactors.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Wedneſd.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bishops.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Whipping.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Patience.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Anger.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For Religious or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Thurſd.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Doctors.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Crowning.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sloath.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For converſion of Infidells.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Frid.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Confeſsors.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Carrying the Croſs.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gluttony</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For ſoules departed.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Saturd.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Virgins.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Crucifying.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Modeſtie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Impurity</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>For diſtreſſed perso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:150050:73"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Woodcut illustration of the crucified Christ, with Mary and John standing either side of the cross (a skull resting at its base).</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
